<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vnfouldyng of sundry vntruths and absurde propositions latelye propounded by one I.B. a greate fauourer of the horrible heresie of the libertimes.</title>
            <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15347</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25631</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103322</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839079</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839079</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3475</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15347)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3475)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1225:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vnfouldyng of sundry vntruths and absurde propositions latelye propounded by one I.B. a greate fauourer of the horrible heresie of the libertimes.</title>
                  <author>T. W. (Thomas Wilcox), 1549?-1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>159, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. Dawson] for Thomas Man,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1581.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: T.W. [i.e. Thomas Wilcox].</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An answeare to B. the Libertine.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Cropped at foot, affecting some signatures; some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>[Banister, J.].</term>
               <term>Theology, Doctrinal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3475:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3475:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> Vnfouldyng of ſundry <hi>vntruths and abſurde</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, latelye propounded <hi>by one I.B. a greate fauourer of</hi> the horrible Hereſie of the <hi>Libertines.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Iohn. 4.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Dearly beloued, beleeue not euery ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, but trie the ſpirites whether they are of God, for,</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iude verſe</hi> 4.</bibl>
               <p>There are certain men crept in, which were before of olde, ordeyned to this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation: Vngodly men they are, which turne the grace of our God into wantonnes, and denie the onely Lord, and our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London for</hi> Thomas Man. 1581.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3475:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader <hi>Grace and peace from</hi> God. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THe dayes are dangerous wherein we liue, and the time of the diſſolution of all thinges draweth nigh, which maketh Satan by himſelfe and his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, dayly more and more to oppoſe him ſelfe againſt the trueth, which if it were not plainely and plentifully prooued by the wonderful ſwarmes of Atheiſtes, Epicures, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts, Pelagians, and the Family of loue, which this our corrupt age doeth vnhappily hatch and ouermuch cheriſh, yet, by the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous and wicked aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this man, in ſome meaſure confuted in this booke, we haue an euident demonſtration and to plaine a proofe. But as this may in ſome meaſure make many ſlide, to ſee ſundry, foſtered in the boſome of the church, who both cloſely &amp; openly goe about to take hir by the throte ſo on the other ſide, this may ſomewhat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort vs, that we may yet behold ſome paſſage graunted to the defence of Gods religion, whileſt that vnder our godly magiſtrates, the confutations of ſuch aſſertious, may be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3475:2"/>freely to paſſe, and be publiſhed. Wherin it is thy duetie (good reader) not onely to ſhew thy ſelfe thankefull to the Lord for this his mercie, but alſo to vſe this and all other holy meanes, to preſerue thy ſelfe ſafe and ſound from this and ſuch like daungerous &amp; deadly infections of thy ſoule, which that thou mayeſt the better performe, I beſeech thee labour diligently in the worde, be ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in prayer vſe continuall meditation, and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent dayly conference, with them, that be ſound and ſincere harted to god &amp; his truth, &amp; then no doubt but vſing that meanes that God hath ordeined, thou ſhalt find his plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful bleſſing vpon thee &amp; thine, not in know ledge onely but in practiſe and obedience al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, which God graunt for his Chriſtes ſake. At London the xxvii. day of this May 1581.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine euer in Chriſt Ieſus T. W. the Lordes moſt vnwoorthie</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3475:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Certaine abſurde and Erroneous <hi>ſpeeches, vttered the xxvi. day of</hi> Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruarie, Anno 1580. by I.B. the Libertine.</head>
            <p n="1">1 THat the firſte Table of the Law, taught vs our duetie towards Chriſts godhead: and the ſecond Table our dueties towards his manhode.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That Chriſt was the Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritane, that holp the wounded man mentioned in Luke.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That fayth was the light of the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That the tree of knowledge of good and euil in Paradiſe, was a figure of Gods Lawe.</p>
            <p>That the tree of life there, was a figure of Gods Goſpell: And that the flaming ſworde was a figure of the threatnings &amp; the iuſtice of god.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That the water in Baptiſme, was not a holy water in reſpect that it was applied to a holy vſe.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3475:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> 6 That the ordinary and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon waſhinges amongſt Turkes &amp; Iewes, was the ſame to them, that Baptiſme is to vs.</p>
            <p n="7">7 That nothing can be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted holie, vnleſſe it be perfect</p>
            <p n="8">8 That Chriſt in his humane ſoule, deſcended into the place of torment appoynted for the wicked, called hell.</p>
            <p n="9">9 That that place of Hel is in the center, that is (as he interpreteth it) in the midle of the earth.</p>
            <p n="10">10 That it is vtterly euill for the Elect, to thinke, ſpeake, or heare of the feare of God.</p>
            <p n="11">11 That Papiſts, Puritans, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and the Familie of loue be vtterly deceaued, and in the ſtate of condemnation, ſaue he alone, and thoſe that take part with him.</p>
            <p n="12">12 That no outward thing (as the workes of ſanctification, vnfey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned forgiueneſſe of others, or ſuch like) can bee pledges, either to our
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3475:4"/>ſelues or others, of our election.</p>
            <p n="13">13 That we may as wel ſay, that Chriſt is fleſh of our fleſh &amp; bones of our bones, as ſay, that we are fleſh of his fleſh, and bones of his bones</p>
            <p n="14">14 That that word kingdom, in the Lords prayer is to be vnderſtod onely of the kingdome of loue and mercy, and not of his kingdome of iuſtice and power,</p>
            <p n="15">15 That Chriſt did not fully fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe but that he ſuffred ſomwhat afterward.</p>
            <p n="16">16 That the laſt woordes that Chriſt ſpake vpon the croſſe, were theſe, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me.</p>
            <p n="17">17 That al the Iewes generally, ſhould be called to the knowledge of God.</p>
            <p n="18">18 That the word Sacrament is not to be found in the ſcripture, and therfore not to be vſed, but the word Record, which hee went about to prooue. 1. Iohn.</p>
            <p n="19">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3475:4"/> 19 That there wil come a time, wherin there ſhalbe no neede of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments in this life: his reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there wil be ſuch multitudes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted, that there ſhalbe no leiſure to miniſter the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p n="20">20. That it is hypocriſie for one chriſtian to reprooue an other for ſwearing, or any ſuch other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, which he calleth but trifles.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1 He ſaid that the firſt Table of the Lawe, taught vs our duetie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes Chriſts Godhead: And the ſecond Table our duetie towardes his manhode.</head>
               <p>THe firſt parte of this aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I confeſſe to be true, becauſe Chriſt being of the ſelfe ſame maieſtie and eſſence with the father, is God equall with him from before all begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and therfore looke what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer appertaineth vnto the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3475:5"/>as god, in worſhip &amp; ſeruice, belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth alſo vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne as he is God: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> latter part is moſt falſe &amp; abſurd. Firſt, becauſe it is vtterly voyd of al grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word, a reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrong &amp; ſufficient enough to ouerthrow, not only this aſſertion, but all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo which haue no better foundation. And ſecondarily, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it followeth vpon it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if murther, which is one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond table, may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hood of our ſauiour Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> then a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may lay violent ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds vpon his bodye alredy glorified in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which howe beaſtly it is too thinke or ſpeake, let the godly iudge.</p>
               <p>But here this fellow hath a ſtatting hole, ſaying that it may be performed &amp; practiſed againſt his members, which are as him ſelfe. Indeede that the lawes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3475:5"/>of the ſecond table, and namely this of murther, may be violated againſt thoſe that are members of Chriſtes bodye, I thinke no man euer denied: but that thoſe members of his, ſhoulde in ſuche ſort be himſelfe, that they ſhould conſtitute &amp; make his humanity &amp; manhood, was neuer yet hard of. And if this ſhould be granted would not this folow vpon it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as we rightly confeſſe &amp; beleeue, that he was in deed borne of the virgine Mary, ſo ſhould we bee borne likewiſe, which is all one with the opinion of the family of loue, though he ſeeme to deteſt it. That there is a very nigh and ſtrait coniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> between Chriſt, as the head, &amp; the faithful as his members, may appeare indeede by ſundry places of ſcripture but that the faithful ſhould be called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>hood of our ſauiour Chriſt which is one of thoſe two ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3475:6"/>&amp; diſtinct natures, that make his holy perſon who is god ouer al to be bleſſed for euer &amp; euer or that his manhod, ſhould be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led his members is very vile, and at no hand to be ſuffered, becauſe thereupon it might bee inferred, that then we were, as the familians ſay, godded with God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2 He ſayde, that Chriſt was the Samaritane that holp the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded man mentioned in Luke. Chap. 10.</head>
               <p>THis hath moſt commonly bin the practiſe of heretiks to allegorize vpon the ſcrip tures, that thereby they might feede the humors of the poore &amp; ſimple people, who thorow their corruption woonderfully delife in ſuch a deformed kinde of han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling the woorde, and alſo that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3475:6"/>they themſelues might ſeeme to haue ſome proofe out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word, though very darke in deed: for the matters they propound and publiſhe, when they haue no plaine places or teſtimonies for the ſame. For mine owne part, I doe vtterly miſlike of this allego<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ricall handling of ſcripture, not only becauſe it hath much defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the true ſence and meaning of Gods holy word, as hee that hath read Origens workes, and ſome others, may eaſily diſcerne but alſo becauſe it hath been the mother to beare and bring forth many beaſtly and baſtardly chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as the opinions of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Familie, doe at this day to the great griefe of many good men ſufficiently prooue.</p>
               <p>But to let this paſſe, and to come to the particular matter in hande, touching this place of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:3475:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Luke, I ſay, that this fellowe hath offered great iniurie to the ſpirite of grace, in going aboute to make the ſcripture ſpeak that which it neuer meant to vtter or ſpeak. That it is a parable plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewing that hee, whom God amongſt men ſtirreth vp to doe good vnto the needy, how far of or how neere ſoeuer he be, ſhould be eſteemed as a neighbour, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that is acquainted with that text and with the ſtory that goeth before it, &amp; the concluſion that our Sauiour inferreth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, may eaſily iudge.</p>
               <p>The Scriptures, eſpecially of the new Teſtament, propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs Parables after two ſorts, ſome are expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vnto vs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, and by peecemeal as it were. Of this ſort there are two mentioned, <hi>Mat. 13.</hi> of the ſower, and of the good ſeede. Wee may
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3475:7"/>ſafely allow of this kind in that place, and in other places where ſoeuer they are found, becauſe, he that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not erre, hath opened the ſame vnto vs. There are other ſome, and theſe are more in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber by many, then the former, as may appear eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that <hi>13.</hi> chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Mathew</hi> before alleadged, which the Lorde hath not parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly expounded, and therfore in them we muſt ſtay our ſelues vpon the general drifte and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thereof, and goe no furher, leaſt wee ſeeme to be wiſe aboue meaſure. For who knoweth not that if it had not beene to haue brideled mans curioſitie, and to haue kept down the pride of his heart, it had byn al one with our ſauiour Chriſt to haue expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded all parables by peecemeale. And of this later ſort is this parable of the Samaritane &amp; the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namded
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3475:8"/>the generall purpoſe wherof hath bin before noted.</p>
               <p>Now hereupon Inferre, that beſides that it bewrayeth won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull preſumption and pride, in the parties ſo handeling the ſcriptures, there was yet neuer any that coulde ſo cunningly alle gorize vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but there was euer one or other abſurditie at the leaſt inſuing therupon. Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting others aſide, let vs take this which we haue preſently in hande. He ſayde that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritaine was Chriſt, doth hee not offer great iniurie, thinke ye to that holy perſon, to reſemble him to ſo vncircumciſed and ſo vnholy a man?</p>
               <p>He ſayth that the two pence ſignified the two Teſtaments, which how abſurd it is may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by this, in that the new Teſtament was not then writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3475:8"/>Beſide I woulde demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of this cold allegorizer, what the wine &amp; the oyle poured into the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, did ſignifie: and whether (if the two pence ſignify the two Teſtaments,) there woulde not follow out of theſe words of the text, ſpoaken to the hoaſt, (take care of him, &amp; whatſoeuer thou ſpendeſt more, when I come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine I will recompence thee,) popiſh traditions and vnwrite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verities? When he ſhal haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered theſe queſtions as alſo who was the hoaſt, what was the Inne, what was his owne beaſt that hee carryed him vpon and what was the prouiſion he made for him, ye ſhall ſee many more abſurdities inſue, and hee himſelfe ſhal then be further an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. And I adde further, that it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the cuſtome of our ſauiour Chriſt: for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3475:9"/>ſpeaketh of himſelfe in parables (as hee doth many times reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble himſelfe to ſundry thinges) that then hee doeth vſually ſay, <hi>I am the good Shepheard, I am the true Vine, I am the Dore, I am the way, the truth and the life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3 He ſaid that faith was the eye, or light of the ſoule.</head>
               <p>BUt I ſay, that if hee woulde haue ſpoken rightlye, hee ſhould rather haue affirmed faith to be the hand of the ſoule, bicauſe that by it only, as it were by a hand, we doe take holde of Chriſt, in whom al the promiſes of God are yea, and Amen, and aplie him and his righteouſues particularlye vnto our ſelues, and this is indeed the true and naturall meaning of this propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3475:9"/>wee are iuſtifyed by fayth only, So much diſputed of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the papiſtes and vs.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, I doe not onely miſlike him for the vnaptnes of his ſpeach, but alſo for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt vntruth and falſhode con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned therin. It is a very cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten rule in reaſon, and allowed of in all artes, that the definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the thing defyned, muſt not be larger one of them than another, for if it be, the definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is naught, and many abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities and vntruthes will inſue therupon: but this definition or deſcription that hee hath giuen of faith, is larger than faith it ſelf (which is the thing defined) as may appeare, becauſe there was neuer yet any in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, but he had ſome light of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoul, &amp; yet not faith: which thing is al ſo more manifeſted vnto vs, by hypocrites in the churche, who
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3475:10"/>haue light and vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding in the ſoule, &amp; yet haue not fayth: for if they had, neither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other could beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it foloweth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or deſcription is falſe &amp; abſurde.</p>
               <p>And for the further proofe of it, wee are to mark, that though the Image of God through the fall of our firſte Parentes was fouly defaced, not only in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but in their poſteritie: yet there was left in them &amp; their ſeede, certain ſparks as it were of light and vnderſtanding, which the Apoſtle in the <hi>8.</hi> to the Romanes, calleth the wiſedom of the fleſhe, affirming that it is enimitie to God, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it is not ſubiect to the law of God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of it ſelf indeed can be. But al this light or vnderſtanding whatſoeuer, ſerueth no further then to make men without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe or defence before God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3475:10"/>the matter of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
               <p>Thirdly I ſay, that for the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>firmation of this his abſurde and falſe aſſertion, he hath fou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie peruerted and wreſted twoo very plaine places of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The firſt is Matth. <hi>6.22, 23.</hi> The other is Hebr. <hi>11.1.</hi> Touching the place of Matt. our Sauiour alleadgeth it, to ſhewe, that men do many times euen maliciouſly and wickedly put out the very light of naturè, that is in them, blearing their eyes and blindfolding ſundrie wayes their owne vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, that they may not behold the thinges, which God preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnto them. Nowe who ſeeth not, that this place, is ſo farre from furthering his aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that it rather proueth the contrarie, to wit,, that many
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3475:11"/>men maye haue light in them, (which they coulde not put out, vnles they had it) &amp; yet. be deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtute of the gifte of faith, which only proceedeth from God. In the other place of the Hebrews, the Apoſtle himſelf giueth a ſure and ſound deſinition of faith, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending the ſame vnto vs, by the excellent effects that it hath to wit, that it doth liuely repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent &amp; expreſſe vnto vs, thinges which yet we hope for, &amp; ſetteth as it were before the eyes of our mindes, thinges that are inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and cannot be ſeen with our bodily eyes. But howe ſerueth this to proue, that euery light of the ſoule is faith? Nay rather how doth it not ouerthrowe it? For many haue had the light of the ſoule as hath beene already proued, yea and at this day ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny haue, as for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3475:11"/>Turkes, &amp;c, which haue not yet for all that atteined this excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t gift of faith. And either the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine muſt confes this, to wit that theſe haue ſome light of the ſoule, &amp; ſo ouerthrow that, which hee ſeemed to confirme, or els af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme men, to be as bruit beaſtes (becauſe men in reſpect of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light &amp; vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beaſts) which is very bruitiſhe indeede. This onely I will ſay, for this time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning this matter, that if he were not vtterly void of the knowledge &amp; vnderſtanding of Gods wil by his word, he wold neuer make ſuch beaſtly conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: ſeeing that we knowe, by Gods word, that the light of the ſoule, is naturally communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to al men, as we confeſſe and beleeue from God: and faith is a ſpecial gift of God, beſtowed not vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al men, but vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> elect only.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3475:12"/>
               <head>4 He ſaid that the tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of good and euill in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe was a figure of Gods lawe: alſo that the tree of life, there, was a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of Gods Goſpel, &amp; laſtly, that the flaming ſword, was a figure of the threatnings and iuſtice of God.</head>
               <p>IF men may be ſuffered in their vain ſpeculatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, thus to ſporte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues with the word of god, and to indeuoure the ſeducinge and deceiuing of others: al reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Lordes trueth wilbe quickly pluckte vp out of mens mindes: and infinite thouſandes caried headlong into eternal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If this be not with the papiſtes, to make a noſe of ware of the ſcriptures, &amp; with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of loue vtterlie to ſubuerte the hiſtories therin co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined, I know not what it is. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree was called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3475:12"/>of good &amp; euil, not becauſe it had good &amp; euil in it of it ſelfe: but good, becauſe it was (as the reſt of the creatures were before ſinne entred) good: and euil bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effecte and conſequent that followed therof. For man (eating of it being forbidden) did by that meanes pull vpon him &amp; his poſteritie, eternal death and condemnation, ſo that it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led euil, in reſpect of the euil, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thorow diſobedience came vpon man and al his race.</p>
               <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree of life, it was ſo called, not becauſe it had life in it ſelf to communicate the ſame to others (for verie abſurd is it to tie ſuch an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t guift, to ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible &amp; vnreaſonable a thing) but becauſe it was appointed by God to ſeale vnto man that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed eſtate of life wherin God pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced him, and continuance in the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3475:13"/>ſame ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as he ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his god. And as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhaking ſword the Lorde ordeined it (together with the cherubins which kept the waye to the tree of life) to ſtrike a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour into Adam and Euah, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fallen: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therby they might vnderſtand, both what excellent benefites, they had depriued themſelues of, and alſo intoo what great miſeries, they had caſt themſelues headlong.</p>
               <p>Nowe this being the onely true and naturall meaning of theſe matters, howe can that ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, which this Libertine hath put downe? If he would needs haue allegorized vpon the tree of life or the reſt, it had bin leſſe euill for him to haue ſaide, that the tree of life, ſhould either haue ſignified God the author of life (becauſe as the Apoſtle
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:3475:13"/>ſaith, in him we liue, moue, and haue our being) or elſe Chriſte himſelfe, who by the working of his ſpirite and power of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, raiſeth vs vp to new<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of life and holy conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> And though I acknowledge this to be true, yet I am not perſwaded, that it can be aptly and fitly gathered out of that place of Geneſis. But further to purſue, the abſurditie of this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legoricall interpretation, and plainely to lay it out to the ſight of the ſimple, wee ſaye, firſt, that he hath bewraied y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great pride and preſumption of his owne hart, becauſe, that wheras it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth onely to the Lorde, too inſtitute and ordain holy ſignes and ſacramentes, and to giue the thinges ſo ordained force &amp; and power, to ſignifie and ſeale the thinges ſignified: this man
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3475:14"/>arrogantly hath taken vppon him this office of God, not only without any warrant from the Lorde himſelfe, but alſo directly contrary to his will reuealed in his woord.</p>
               <p>Secondarily he hath woon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully manifeſted, the beaſtlie blindneſſe and ignorance of his heart: for, whereas in all ſignes and ſacramentes, there ſhould be euer a certaine analogie and proportion, betweene the ſignes and the thinges ſignified, there can be no ſuch thinge founde out betweene the tree of knowledge of good and euil, and the lawe of God it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Beſides, what blockiſhnes doth this argue in him, to reſemble y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tree of knowledg of good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, to the whole law of God, &amp; the ſhaking ſword to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges of God, as though for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3475:14"/>the whole did not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende the partes? And if this mans vaine ſhoulde be followed, we ſhould not onely haue ſeuen ſacramentes (as the Papiſtes imagine) but ſeuentie times ſeuen, that is infinite and innumerable. But of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ynough if not to much.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>5 He ſayth, that the water in Baptiſme was in no reſpect to bee ſayde or counted a holy water, no not in reſpect it was applyed to a holy vſe.</head>
               <p>THis Aſſertion greatly bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraieth, firſt his groſſe ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance in the woord of God For why may not the water in baptiſme be eſteemed and ſaide to be a holy water, as well as the prieſtes garmentes, the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the mountaines and other
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3475:15"/>thinges were ſayde to be holy? When we ſay the water in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is a holy water we meane not that it hath any holineſſe in it ſelfe, or that it is made holie, by any magicall incantation as the Papiſtes dreame) but ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king according to the vſe of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture which cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth euery thing holy that by Gods appointment is ſeparated from prophane and common vſes, and dedicated &amp; applyed by his inſtitution to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſes. And therfore we feare not to affirme (whatſoeuer this babler ſhall ſay to the contrary) that the water in baptiſme is a holy water, not onely becauſe it is dedicated to a holy vſe, but al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo becauſe it proceedeth from a holy inſtitutor, and is by his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, appointed to ſeale and ſet foorth vnto vs, holy thinges to witte the waſhing away of al
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3475:15"/>our ſinnes, in the death &amp; blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhedding of our Sauiour: and our riſing vp to righteouſneſſe &amp; wel doing, by the vertue &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his reſurrection from the dead.</p>
               <p>Secondarily, it manifeſteth in what baſe regard and account he hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sacraments of God, which may appeare not only by this, but by ſundrie other ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches vttered by him: as that the Iewes may receiue as much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, by their ordinary and common waſhinges, as wee by baptiſme. Beſides, that there ſhal bee a time in this life, wherein there ſhal be no neede of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and ſuch like, of which wee will ſpeake hereafter in their ſeuerall places.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>6 That the ordinary and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon waſhings amongſt the Turkes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3475:16"/>and Iewes, were the ſame to them, that Baptiſme is to vs.</head>
               <p>THis carrieth with it, in the iudgement of al vpright me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, greate preſumption of prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in that he dare make equall with the Sacrament of baptiſm not the ordinary and common waſhinges of Chriſtians, but euen of Turks and Iewes, who before GOD are as Infidels, becauſe they acknowledge him not, in the perſon of his ſonne and withall ſauoreth very ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Sacramentary hereſie: yea it is far more abſurde and vile, becauſe the Sacramenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, ſpeaking indeede very baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie of the Sacramentes, that is, eſteeming them but as bare cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies &amp; ſignes of holy things, did yet neuer ſo farre extenuate or debaſe the ſame, as to reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3475:16"/>them (hauing their inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from God) to common &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane things, vſed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt ſuch, as becauſe they are voyde of faith, are iuſtly condemned in &amp; for the thinges they doe.</p>
               <p>And note withall the ſubtletie and malice of Sathan, who ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng he cannot carry me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> headlo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g into deſtruction, by ouermuch re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, either in iudgment or acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Sacraments, with the Papiſts and Lutherans on the one ſide: nor yet thorowe an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right &amp; an vnreuerent opinion of the ſacramentes with the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other ſide: hath at the laſt ſtirred vp this wicked inſtrument, by a new aſſaulte, to batter their faith, and to plunge them ouer heade and eares, into eternal deſtruction. But as I hope that they which are rightly inſtructed of God, by his word &amp;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3475:17"/>ſpirit, wil looke to themſelues, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they bee not ſurpriſed with this diueliſh perſuaſion: ſo I humbly beſeech the reſt, that haue not as yet atteined to ſo greate a mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure &amp; light of vnderſtanding, to take heede, that they doe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be ware, drinke in and that to their vtter ruine, this deadly poyſon of their ſoules which carrieth with it ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt a conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of the order of God, and by conſequent contempt of his Maieſtie, becauſe no deſpite can be offered vnto his ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but the iniurie thereof, doeth in ſome meaſure redounde vnto himſelfe.</p>
               <p>And indeed to ſpeake the truth if our baptiſme haue no ſinguler priuiledge aboue the ordinary &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon waſhings vſed amongſt Turkes &amp; Iewes, our Sauiour Chriſt hath dealte vnaduiſedly,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3475:17"/>that I may ſay no more, to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie him ſelfe ſo much about the inſtitution of newe ſacraments in the newe ſtate of the Church and to occupy the harts, heads, hands, and euery part and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, both of the miniſters admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the ſame, and of the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple communicating therein. For my parte I thinke godlines and wiſedome woulde teach vs to preuent (what we may) after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claps for if this man may be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered ſo defacing the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, why may he not likewiſe offer diſgrace vnto the worde? And if he may diſgrace the woorde, why may he not in like ſorte, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace God the author thereof: and ſo not onelie a wide dore ſet open to al atheiſtrie, but alſo the verie foundations therof pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted and layd. But (I hope) the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly magiſtrates, wil in time haue
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3475:18"/>an eye to theſe inconueniencies, that at the leaſt, if they cannot be vtterly rooted out, yet they ſhal not ſpread their vowes and braunches further abrode.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>7 He ſayth that nothing can be counted holy, vnleſſe it bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</head>
               <p>I Woulde faine learne what can be more repugnant to the holy ſcripture then this aſſertion. Do wee not reade that many, both thinges &amp; men, are called holy in the ſcriptures, as <hi>Exodus. 35.21.</hi> the garmentes of the Prieſts are called holy. Alſo <hi>Exod. 19.6.</hi> the people are called a holy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God.</p>
               <p>But I know, becauſe I haue heard this fellow ſpeake, that he thinketh eaſilie too ſhifte of all
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3475:18"/>theſe and infinit number of ſuch like places becauſe they are writ ten in the old Teſtament. How right this anſwere is, let euery godly man iudge, not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee knowe, that certaine among the Anabaptiſtes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore laboured, as alſo this fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe now doth, to impayre &amp; to diſanul the authoritie of the old Teſtament: but alſo becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit it ſelf beareth record, that whatſoeuer thinges were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before hand, were written for our learning, vpon whome the ends of the world are come, that we through patience and comfort of the ſcripture might haue hope. And that this truth might be indeede, the more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually ratified and confirmed vnto vs, we haue the practiſe &amp; example of Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who for the confirmation
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3475:19"/>of their doctrines, haue allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged teſtimonies and examples out of the old teſtament, which they would not haue done, if the olde Teſtament had been vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abrogated, as thoſe fantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſpirits haue dreamed.</p>
               <p>But admit that this copper woulde goe for currant coyne, The Lorde hath not ſo ſkanted vs, but that wee haue a cloude of witneſſes, euen in the newe Teſtament, to ouerthrowe this falſhoode. Saint Peter calleth the mount, whereuppon Chriſt was tanſfigured, holy, Saint Iude calleth the fayth of Gods children, not only holy, but moſt holy. How many times doeth Saint Paule and Sainte Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, call all ſuch as are gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into the boſome or lappe of the Churche by the woorde of preaching, and the miniſterie of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3475:19"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame (whether they are men women, or children) Saintes or holy ones. For the proofe hereof, turne to theſe places fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. <hi>Rom. 1.7. 1. Corin. 7.14 1. Tim. 5.10. 1 Pe. 1 16. 1. Pe. 3.5.</hi> &amp; many other ſuch like: and yet wee knowe that they were clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with corruption and had ſinne, though not raigning, yet dwelling in them, whatſoeuer this fanaticall fellow wil ſay to the contrary.</p>
               <p>True, yea moſt true is that ſpeech of the Apoſtle, we knowe in part &amp; wee propheſy in parte, but when that which is perfect is come, then that which is in part ſhalbe aboliſhed. I ſuppoſe that this man, muſing and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſo much of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this life, iumpeth flatly with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie of loue, howeſoeuer hee would ſeem much to diſlike the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3475:20"/>and hath had ſome large confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with A.C.S. who doteth and deliuereth much concerning this matter in his Dialogues vpon the Romanes.</p>
               <p>Whatſoeuer it bee wee feare not too condemne it as a groſſe and deteſtable error, putting flaxe to the fire of mans preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and proud nature in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye and being a terrible heade-long downe fall into deſperation to otherſome, while they ſee and finde in them ſelues, that they cannot atteine in this life to the ſame. But to ſuch mens com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort it ſhall bee verie good for them, not onely not once too admitte ſuch a thought, as that they maye atteine too perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this life (a marke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede whereat wee muſt aime, though verily we cannot hit the ſame) but vtterly to eſtraunge
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3475:20"/>it farre from them ſtaying them ſelues vpon this, that all their imperfections are couered in the fulnes of Chriſtes perfection, and that though they cannot at<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teine by reaſon of their owne weaknes, to perfect faith, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect hope, to perfect repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to perfect mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c. Yet they doe thorough gods great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, atteine to the ſoundnes and truth; of many excellent and woorthie graces, as too haue ſtedfaſt faith, true repentance, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And thus much I thought good to put downe, leaſt either on the one ſide, wee might bee ouerthrowne in our wantes, or on the other ſide be deceiued in a falſe imagination of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For heere wee ſayle in a daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous gulfe, and paſſe as it were betweene twoo greate
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3475:21"/>rocks or cleffes, if either of which we touch, we are in perill with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods riche mercie helpe, of eternall deſtruction, both of body and ſoule.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>8 He ſaith that Chriſt in his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſoule, deſcended into the place of torment, appointed for the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked called hell. <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. pag.</hi> 118. 127.</head>
               <p>WHat great varietie of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions &amp; mindes: there is concerning this Article, hee that is acquaynted with Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mens writinges, may eaſily perceiue. For mine owne parte, ſetting aſide all partialtie &amp; dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling againſt any, ſaue this perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious man, I will bee as briefe &amp; ſhort in it as poſſible I man.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing that I haue to ſaye of it is this, that for as much as Saint <hi>Cyprian</hi> an aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3475:21"/>father of the Church plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie affirmeth, that neither the Romaine nor Eaſte Churches had this point in their confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of faith at all: and for as much as no confeſſion of faith at all, ſo farre as I remember, penned in generall councels as that of <hi>Nice,</hi> of <hi>Epheſus, Chalce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don &amp;c.</hi> toucheth it any whit, but vtterly omitteth the ſame: And for aſmuch as the other Articles of our beliefe, may euen in plaine words be pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed, out of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, and yet there is no ſuch either word or meaning (as the Papiſts drawe out of it) to bee founde in the bookes of the olde and new Teſtament, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſeemeth vnto mee not to bee a matter of any great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, ſo that it bee expounded according to the Analogie and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3475:22"/>proportion of faith.</p>
               <p>And though it bee true, that this felow in this point of Chriſt his deſcent into hell, bee not ſo groſſe as other ſome are, who imagine that hee went downe thither, to harrow it as it were and too fetche from thence the ſoules of ſuche of the faythfull fathers, as dyed before Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes death: yet (as ſhall appeare by that which followeth) he is very vnſounde in the ſame. For to ſay that Chriſte in his h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Soule deſcended into the place of the damned, is quite and cleane contrarie too that ſpeeche of Chriſte vppon the Croſſe, when hee cryed ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Father into thy handes I commende my Spirite, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding by the woorde ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, his ſoule, and by commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it into the handes of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3475:22"/>God his father, the returning of the ſame, into the hands of God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gaue it, of which ſee <hi>Eccle. 12.7.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And his beaſtlineſſe is ſo much the more intellerable, by howe much he abuſeth ſome places of ſcripture, for the maintenance of this his abſurd aſſertion. He al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged indeed foure ſpeciall pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherof two were taken out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old feſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and twoo out of the newe. The firſt place out of the olde is. <hi>Leu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 16.</hi> Where he intreateth of the ſcape grate: the other is <hi>Pſalme 86.13.</hi> The places out of the new teſtament be. <hi>Rom. 10.6.7. Epſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 6.4.8.9.</hi> of which places we mind to ſpeake particularly.</p>
               <p>Concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of <hi>Leuit.</hi> he would gather it by an al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the frape goa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted by the Lord to be let go into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wildernes would be a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3475:23"/>of Chriſt, eſcaping free out of hel, reſembling the Wilderneſſe too hell, which wilderneſſe he ſaieth (but there is no ſuch warrant for it in the Text) was ful of wilde, rauenous &amp; deuouring beaſtes: but the abſurditie of this allego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie appeareth, becauſe not the ſcape Goate ſo much, but the Goate that was appointed to be the peoples ſinne offering (if anye of them were a figure of Chriſt) was the figure rather. Beſides, it is ſpoken without al grounde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Text in that place, that the wilderneſſe was full of wilde heaſtes. I ſuppoſe that a man may more ſafely ſay, that it was called a wildernes, becauſe it was by muche leſſe inhabited then other, partes of the lande were, and ſo is the worde taken, <hi>Math. 3.1.</hi> Where it is faide, that Iohn <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eached in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3475:23"/>of <hi>Iudea,</hi> which muſt be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, not as ſome of Saint <hi>Frauncis</hi> order haue thought, as though hee had preached to the trees and beaſtes of the forreſts, but becauſe he preached in thoſe places which were leſſe inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted then other quarters of the lande were.</p>
               <p>Touching the place of <hi>Pſal. 86.13.</hi> I ſay, that it is as muche peruerted &amp; abuſed as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Which ſhall appeare, if we doe but a litle conſider the words and circumſtances. The wordes lye thus: for thy mercie is great towardes me, and thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered my ſoule from the loweſt graue. Which verſe I take to be a reaſon, why Dauid woulde praiſe the Lorde with his whole hearte and glorifie his name for euer, to witte, becauſe God had woonderfully deliuered him (for
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3475:24"/>he putteth his ſoule (which is a part of him for his whole man) fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very imminent &amp; infinite da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, which hee vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth by the terme of loweſt graue. And this ſenſe is plaine, not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Dauid made the Pſalme being ſore diſtreſſed, ſometimes with inward afflictions, &amp; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with outwarde perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by the extreeme outrage &amp; furie of his enimies, in the dayes of his life vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth: but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, if it were not ſo, this abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie and inconuenience woulde enſue therupon, that Dauid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, and condemned into the place of torment, ſhoulde bee deliuered therefrom, and ſet in the place of eternall bleſſednes, which is not onelye quite and cleane contrary, to the ſcope and drift of holie Scriptures (as ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peareth.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3475:24"/>
                  <hi>Luke 16.26.</hi>) But vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlye ſubuerteth the iuſtice of GOD, and accuſeth it ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of inconſtancie or raſhneſſe, as though that hee had, either vnaduiſedly pronounced a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, or were not conſtant in his counſelles, and ſtedfaſt in the performance of his purpoſes and wayes.</p>
               <p>Touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Rom. 10.</hi> He hath bewrayed verie groſſe and palpable ignoraunce, beyng deceiued belike with the bare ſhew of the wordes, deſcend into the deepe. For if he out of this place would proue Chriſtes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent into hell, an other might as eaſilie and with better reaſon by muche, prooue his aſcention into heauen, but in truth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place doth not plainly prooue, neither the one nor the other. The true and naturall meaning of thoſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3475:25"/>wordes of Saint Paule, I take to be this that Paul ſetteth that peace of conſcience, which the righteouſneſſe of faith bringeth with it, againſt all their perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and doubtfull thoughts, that ſeeke and hunt after the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of the law. And theſe y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations or thoughtes, are two ſolde in them, whileſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they think, how they may auoyde condemnation, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times whileſt they thinke, how they may obtayne eternall life and ſaluation. For the lawe propounding heauen no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but by an impoſſible condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and threatning death and deſtruction for the breach of the ſame, it muſt neceſſarily folowe, that euery one that ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth ſtiffe in the righteouſneſſe of the law, muſt be inforced to crie out, who ſhall aſcend into heauen? to wit,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3475:25"/>that hee may bring mee thither. Or who ſhall deſcende into the deepe? to wit, to deliuer me from the ſame. But the righteouſnes of faith telleth vs, that Chriſte, hauing fulfilled all righteouſnes for vs, &amp; hauing ſuffered for vs, the puniſhment which was due vnto vs, ouercomming in his death, death it ſelf, and him that had the power of death, that is, the Diuell, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might bring vs to heauen alſo, that where he is as the head, we might be as the members. And if this were not the true ſenſe (as indeede there can be no other but it) yet were not his collection out of theſe wordes right and ſound, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe it would follow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon, that Chriſte woulde bee brought out of heauen, but alſo that he is euen yet at this day in ſome ſort, to be brought again
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3475:26"/>from the dead: and ſo not onlie the trueth of his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denied, but he helde vnder of death, and the ſorowes thereof, which S. Peter affirmeth <hi>Act.</hi> the ſeconde, to bee an impoſſible thing.</p>
               <p>Nowe a worde or two concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the place out of the <hi>Epheſi.</hi> In the former verſes, S. Paule had laboured to perſwade the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians,</hi> to ſuch vnity &amp; concord, as God alloweth of: and that he might the better performe this, he ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God in Chriſt hath giuen ſundrie gifts to his church and the particular members therof for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great &amp; excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, &amp; this is put downe in the ſeuenth verſe. Nowe that Chriſt hath giuen ſuch graces to his Church, he proueth it, by a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, borowed out of Dauid. The woordes as they lie in the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3475:26"/>text are theſe: wherefore he ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth (that is the holie Ghoſt) by the pen &amp; mouth of his ſeruaunt Dauid) when hee aſcended vp on highe (that is, roſe againe from death, and went vp into heauen) he laide captiuitie cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue (that is, hee made ſuch his captiues &amp; ſlaues, as had before healde others in captiuity and thraldome, meaning thereby the Diuel, death, ſinne, &amp; whatſoeuer els did ſet it ſelfe againſt Chriſt &amp; his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers. Al know that vnder a metaphor in this place, there is excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly deſcribed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> triumph of Chriſt our Conqueror, S. Paule therein alluding, to the maner of earthly Conquerors, who after ſome victory atteined, were ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nely &amp; triumphantly receyued into the places whether they came, their captiues going either before the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or behind the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chained.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3475:27"/>And that he might the better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the glorious conqueſt of our Sauiour Chriſt, he ſaith not ſimplie, hee leade the captiues, but that he leade captiuitie cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, ſpeaking accordiug to the proprietie of the Hebrue tongue, vſing the Abſtracte, that is, the ſubſtantiue, for the concrete, that is the Adiectiue, ſignifying ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo, the greate multitude of enemies, that hee carried with him as captiues: and he that is but meanely ſeene, either in the Scriptures, or in the Hebrewe tongue, will eaſily acknowledge the trueth of this. It follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, And gaue giftes vnto men (to wit, for the continuall helpe and comfort one of them of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; al tending to the building vp of the bodie of Chriſte, which is his Churche) <hi>verſ. 9.</hi> Nowe in that he aſcended (to wit, into
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3475:27"/>heauen) what is it (that is, what meaneth it.) But that hee had alſo deſcended, firſt into the loweſt parts of the earth. Theſe are the woordes that this Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine moſt preſſeth, that is the loweſt partes of the earth. But I anſweare, that hee much abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth theſe wordes: for the worde earth, is not taken here onely for this world wheron men walke, but alſo for the whole world com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehending heauen, earth, and whatſoeuer els: and ſo thoſe wordes, the loweſt partes of the earth carrie with them this ſeuſe, that Chriſt deſcended fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the glorie of his father into the earth, which is indeede the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the whole worlde, for fire, a yre, water and al are high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it. Beſides, if theſe words (loweſt parts of the earth) ſhuld be taken for hell, this abſurditie
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3475:28"/>would follow vpon it, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dauid ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was made in a ſecrete place, and faſhioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath in the earth (or as it is in the Hebrew text) In the lower parts of the earth, that when he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>uld haue byn made, conceiued, and borne in hel, then the which, what can be more abſurde? But as this fellowe hath byn fowlie deceaued, in alleadging of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, for the maintenaunce of his error: ſo he is as much deceiued and more alſo in the matter it ſelfe. For the truth is ſo farre of, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propounding any ſuch groſſe thing concerning our Sauiour, Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it teacheth vs, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> as he did indeed ſuffer a natural death (which is the ſundring of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die &amp; ſoule for a time) ſo he was both in bodie and ſoule, ſhut vp in woonderful diſtreſſe: in bodie, when being in agonie, his ſweete
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3475:28"/>was like droppes of blood, trick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe to the ground. <hi>Luke. 22.44.</hi> And in ſoule, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaid, my ſoule is very heauy, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death. <hi>Mat. 26.38.</hi> And when he cried out vpon the croſſe, my God my God why haſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me. <hi>Math. 27.46.</hi> And al theſe layde together, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saint Peter calleth the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of death. <hi>Actes. 22.24.</hi> which he ſuffered for vs miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinners, whileſt that hee preſented himſelfe to the iuſtice and iudgement of his Father, to the ende that hee might ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſame for vs: So that neceſſary was it, that he ſhould in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, feele this feareful agonye and condemnation as it were, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as though he had byn forſaken of GOD his father, and he had byn angry with him
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:3475:29"/>bearing our ſinnes vppon his backe. And this I take too bee the naturall meaning of this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle. <hi>Hee deſcended into hell,</hi> that hee did in his very ſufferinges and death, not onelie ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe againſt all our enimies, as the world, the fleſhe, the Diuell and eternall condemnation: but did, as it were, wraſtle euen ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to hande with them, ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them all for vs, that we, (by the vertue and power of his victorie) might bee more then Conquerors, And thus much I thought good to put downe, as my ful perſuaſion grounded and ſetled vpon Gods woorde, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this point: being readie to yeeld to any other, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can ſhew further out of the word of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>9 That that place of Hel is in the Center, that is, as hee himſelfe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3475:29"/>alſo interpreteth it, in the middle of the earth.</head>
               <p>Mans curiouſneſſe of the one ſide, &amp; his ignorance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, hath beene, is, and ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be, the cauſe of a bottomleſſe pit of errour, and corruption. If we had no other thing to prooue it by, yet that which hath byn held and propounded, concerning the place of hell, and the manner of tormentes in the ſame, were ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient enough to confirme that which hath byn ſaide.</p>
               <p>Concerning the paines and puniſhmentes of it, I minde to ſay nothing at this time becauſe it concerneth not the queſtion we haue in hand. But concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the place, thus much I ſay that it is fautaſticall curiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe at the leaſt, if not an intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable pride, for anye man too
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:3475:30"/>take vppon him to pointe out where that place ſhould be, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Lorde, hath not in any place of the olde and newe Teſtament declared the ſame.</p>
               <p>That ſuch a place there is, prepared of old for the diuel and his angels, and the reprobate, the ſcripture declareth. But where it ſhoulde be, or in what place, as whether in the center of the earth, or in ſome region of the ayre, or in ſome of the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt partes of the world, it is not reuealed, no more then the certaine time either of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or of the fall of the Angels. Wherefore as we doe in al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſobrietie, beleeue that they were created, and beleeue that they did fall, becauſe the worde of God doeth warrant the ſame vnto vs (notwithſtanding that the time eyther of the one
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3475:30"/>or of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other be not put down:) ſo it behooueth vs, with the like meaſure of chriſtian modeſtie, to behaue our ſelues in this point, that ſeing we know ſuch a place of torment ther is, wee ſhoulde beleeue that, and yet becauſe we knowe not, where particularly it is ſett, we ſhoulde beware of raſhe and haſtie pronouncing of any thing, concerning the ſame For as the reuealed counſelle of the Lord, apperteineth to vs and our poſteritie, to knowe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and doe the ſame: ſo wee may not enter into thoſe ſecrets, that his maieſtie hath kept cloſe vnto himſelfe, leaſt we be for our preſumption, vtterly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded &amp; ouer whelmed of his glory.</p>
               <p>And me thinketh, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> if we had not theſe reaſons take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the word to bridle our curioſitie, yet euen in verie chriſtian pollicie,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:3475:31"/>it ſhould ſtande vs in hande, for the preuenting of greater after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claps, to laye a ſtop here, and in all ſuch carious queſtions what ſoeuer. For if one may be fuffred in the vaine and ydle imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his owne hearte and heade to diſcourſe without the warrant of the word, vpon this or any other ſuch like point, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king reſolute and flat concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning the ſame. Why ſhall it not be lawful, for others to doe the like? And ſo by that meanes, we ſhall haue a whole worlde of mens fantaſies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded vnto vs, and in proceſſe of time, (mans nature being gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>die of noueltie) Gods truth and the groundes and principles of the ſame, if not vtterly defaced &amp; diſcredited, yet wonderfully im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payred and abaſed. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bothe magiſtrates and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3475:31"/>are in this reſpecte too haue a vigilant eye, in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſtop the gap to theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, and to keepe ſhort ſuch perſons as this is, who dare ſo ſhameleſly propound ſuch hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſteries and erroneous opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>10 That it is vtterly euil for the elect to thinke, ſpeake, or heare of the feare of God.</head>
               <p>THe trueth is ſo farrè of from admitting, either in truth or ſhew, any ſuch blaſphemous &amp; beaſtly ſpeech, as this is, that it doeth in flat and plaine termes, put down a plaine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. A notable proofe hereof we haue in this earneſt and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wiſh, of the Lord teſtifying thereby his mercie and greate good will towardes his people,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3475:32"/>ſaying. O that there were ſuch a heart in them to feare me, and to keepe al my commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts alway, that it might goe well with them, and with their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren foreuer. Which (if the feare of his maieſtie had bin euill,) he woulde neuer haue done. This alſo appeareth, by that moſte mercifull promiſe that hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vnto his owne people, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: I will giue them one hearte, and one way that they maye feare mee for euer (and not at any time as this Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine ſayeth) for the wealth of them, and of their children after them.</p>
               <p>By whiche woordes it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that the right reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and feare GOD, beeing ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely planted in the heartes of his children, is ſo farre of from woorking any hurt or da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:3475:32"/>vnto his Saintes, that it is rather a pledge and an aſſured teſtimonie of his loue and fauoure, not vntoo them onely, but euen vnto their verie iſſue and poſteritie.</p>
               <p>I woulde bee loth to charge this fellowe further than trueth, neither haue I hitherto gone beyonde the boundes thereof. For myne owne part, I reſt perſwaded, and I hope I ſhall haue the approbation of ſuche as bee ſingly ſighted in the matters of GOD, with mee that this aſſertion is not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye repugnaunt too the trueth of the woorde (as hath beene before ſhewed) but that it doeth by a conſquente carye with it, not one, but many moſte horrible blaſphemies.</p>
               <p>Firſt if this ſhould be true what
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3475:33"/>ſhoulde we doe with ſo infinite numbers of places in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which doe exact and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde this feare towardes God of vs, but vtterly blot the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the book of gods word &amp; caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away? And woulde not then this follow vpon it, that if we reiect apart of the woord, we may ſafely reiect the whole. For why ſhoulde wee allowe of one part &amp; refuſe another? Or who hath giuen vs any ſuch pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like authoritie? And then alſo would not this enſue: that men might likewiſe (the woord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſt away) denie God the au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thor of life? A point which the Atheiſtes of our age doe very much vrge &amp; preſſe, as by words and deedes appeareth very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly, to ſuch as are acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with their aſſertions and dealinges.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:3475:33"/>
               <p> Beſide, doth it not flatly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe, not onely the iuſtice of GOD, which ſhould ſerue as a bridle to keepe vs from euill, if he ſhoulde not be feared, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the mercie of GOD, which ſhould be a ſpurre to prouoke vs to wel doing? Notable is that place of the Prephete Dauid. Mercie is with thee that thou maiſt be feared. For the children of God or elected people (of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this fellowe ſeemeth to ſpeake) are ſo farre of from receiuing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hurt or euill, by meditating, ſpeaking, or hearing of the feare of Gods maieſtie, that they reape and receiue thereby ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler profite. For as Gods mercie, is a ſinguler argument or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſpirituall ioy vnto them, in the dayes of any their heauineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or diſtreſſes either outward or inwarde. So the reuerent
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3475:34"/>feare of Gods Maieſtie, in the times of their greate peace and proſperity, which it pleaſeth him ſometimes to geue vnto them, is a notable meane to inſtruct them, to take heede vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that they bee not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried forwarde, eyther by the pleaſures, or by the profites of this life, to the thinking, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, or doyng of any thing that may bee diſpleaſing before God, or vnanſweareable to that great calling wherein hee hath placed them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it taketh away one of the ſeales and pledges of our repentance, &amp; ſo by that meanes ſhaketh our faith, which we had neede to labour, to prop, and ſtay vp, by all the lawfull and holie meanes we can, which God him ſelfe hath ordeined and ſet foorth vnto vs in his worde to vſe: ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3475:34"/>if wee woulde but with a ſingle eye, conſider, either our owne weakneſſe on the one ſide, or the ſtrength, ſubtletie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall aſſaultes of our ſpiritual enimies on the other ſide. Saint Paule <hi>2. Cor. 7.11.</hi> prooueth that a reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t feare of God, wrought in our heartes, by the ſight of our former ſinnes, and the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of his iuſtice againſt vs for the ſame, is a ſinguler effecte and declaration, of our vnfained repentaunce and amendment (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as ſome good fruite is a playne proofe of a good tree) whileſt that, conſidering our owne ſlipperines on the one ſide and Gods heauie indignation &amp; wrath agaynſt vs for ſinne on the other ſide, wee doe with care &amp; conſcience, not only looke vnto our ſteppes, that wee fall
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3475:35"/>not into the like miſchiefes: but alſo ſtriue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vttermoſt of our powers, both to the purpoſe and performa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, of ſuch good works, as hee himſelfe hath prepared that we ſhould walke in.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, this aſſertion, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth open a wide gate, to all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſſe and licentiouſneſſe. For if God be not to be feared in reſpect of his iudgement, euen as he is to be loued for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, men may then liue as they liſt, which bridle, if it bee once layde in the neckes of outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and vnruely people (as you ſee all are, to prone that way) what miſchiefe and ſinne, will not enſue thereuppon? For my owne part, I am ſo farre from approouing this mans opinion, that I thinke it moſt meete and conuenient, for the children of God, to haue often before their
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3475:35"/>eyes, not onely that ſame filiall or childiſh feare (which ariſeth of a certaine reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Gods ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in their hearts,) hauing an vnfeigned loue of the ſame, as an inſeparable companion an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed vnto it) but alſo that ſame ſeruile feare, or feare of ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, which ſpringeth from the terror of his iudgements, &amp; the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of his iuſtice.</p>
               <p>And the reaſon that leadeth me thereto is this, becauſe that as it is meete, for the ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and vpholding of our faith, againſt ſpirituall combates and aſſaultes that men ſhoulde ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnto themſelues, as muche ſtrength out of the word, and as many heauenly comfortes, as poſſiblie they may, becauſe that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we come to the conflict, we ſhall haue neede of them all: ſo vp reaſon of the proneneſſe and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3475:36"/>inclination that is in vs, to all maner of ſinne before regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of an ouerwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wee haue of our ſelues and of our owne workes (as the pride of our owne heartes doth ſufficiently prooue it vnto vs, and the palpable opinion of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath crept in in popery, doeth plainly declare it) and by reaſon alſo of the great ſea of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie and careleſnes, wherein men are drowned, in theſe ſame laſt and dangerous daies of the world: it ſhalbe good for euery one to gather to himſelfe, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny meanes as poſſibly he can to ſtay him from following the ſwinge of ſinne, and as manie ſwoordes as hee may, to cutte downe the opinion of pride, and preſumption that wee carrie in our ſelues, and as many trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets of terrors &amp; threatning, to
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:3475:36"/>arrowſe and wake vs out of the dead ſleepe of careleſnes and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity. Which thinges wee can neuer performe, if wee ſhake of once, this ſame eaſie and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble yoke of the reuerent feare of Gods maieſtie.</p>
               <p>And herein I am not alone: for the Apoſtle Paul writing to the <hi>Romaines</hi> (vpon whom God at that time had ſhewed the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his grace, in vouchſafing to make them the veſſelles of his mercie) doeth notwithſtanding admoniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to take heed that they bee not high minded, but feare: and the reaſon of this his exhortation is this, for if GOD ſpared not the naturall braunches, take heede leaſt hee alſo ſpare not thee admoniſhing them as it were to haue all eye to the feare of God, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might be conteyned and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:3475:37"/>kepte within the compaſſe of a good conuerſation, anſwerable to that greate grace of election, that God had beſtowed vppon them. Which thing the Apoſtle ſhould not haue needed to haue done, if the aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this lewd Libertine, had had any ground of truth at all in it?</p>
               <p>But that this fellowe, might not ſeem to ſpeake without war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, he hath laboured to pull, and that by the eares, into the wreſtling place, twoo Textes of Scripture, fowlie peruerted, for the maintenance of this, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable error. The one is taken out of the <hi>Pſalme. 18.44.</hi> The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of <hi>Eſay. 54.4.14.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The woordes of the <hi>Pſalme</hi> are theſe: Straungers ſhall ſhrinke away and feare in their priuie chambers. Howe theſe woordes ſhoulde proue, that the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:3475:37"/>elect, ſhoulde be vtterly voyde of the feare of God, no man in his right wittes (as I ſuppoſe) can rightly coniecture or iudge, The meaning of the Prophet is this: that foraſmuch, as hee was the Lordes annoynted, the Lord woulde ſo woorke for him and by him, that not onely his owne people, ſhoulde bee brought in ſubiection, but euen fortainers and ſtraungers that were not vnder his iuriſdiction and gouernment, ſhould be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued by his power: and that for the better accompliſhment here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the heartes of his enemies, ſhoulde bee ſtricken and ſeaſed, with ſuch horror and feare, that they ſhoulde haue little, or no power at all to reſiſt or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him. So that you ſee, that this place prooueth, that the feare of men ſhalbe in the hearts
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:3475:38"/>of the wicked, but that the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhould haue no feare of God, at al in them, or that it ſhould be hurtefull for them, to thinke, ſpeake, or heare of the ſame, ther is not ſo much as one ſillable or iot tending to that end.</p>
               <p>The wordes of the Prophet Eſay are theſe, Feare not, for thou ſhalt not be aſhamed, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhalt thou be confounded: And againe, in righteouſneſſe ſhalt thou be eſtabliſhed, and be far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oppreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, (for thou ſhalt not feare it) &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> feare, for it ſhall not come neere thee. They that will looke with diligence into the chapter, ſhall finde, that the ſpeciall purpoſe and drifte of the prophet, is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte the church which ſhoulde bee collected and gathered of the Iewes &amp; Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, but ſpecially of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles, not to be afraid for any terror or
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:3475:38"/>perſecution, that the enemies therof could practiſe or perfourm agaynſt them: ſo that I take it to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame in meaning, though vttered at another time and in other woordes, which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh <hi>Phillip. 1.28.</hi> In no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing feare your aduerſaries, which is to them a token of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, but to you of ſaluation, &amp; that of God: and alſo the ſame which our ſauiour himſelf ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, when he ſayth. <hi>Matt. 10.28.</hi> Feare ye not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which kil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die &amp; are not able to kill y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule, but rather feare him which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to deſtroy both bodie &amp; ſoule in hell, which place ſerueth, not onely to ſhewe the true ſence &amp; meaning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place vntruely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged: but alſo to teach, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there ought to be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearts of gods childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, a feare of gods maieſtie.</p>
               <p>And thus you ſee that this
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:3475:39"/>place thus alleadged ſerueth lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing to the purpoſe it was alleaged for, to witte, that the elect ſhould baniſh far from them, all hearing and ſpeaking of the feare of God, and not ſo much, as to admit one thought of the ſame, if it were poſſible, ſeeing that the Prophets pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is, to teach the elect, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue farre from them, onely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of men, which to weake fleſh and blood, if it be not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weighed with ſpiritual ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth from aboue is a terrible thing, to turne men backe, from the bolde imbracing and profeſſing of Gods holy religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>11 That Papiſts, Puritans, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and the Familie of loue be vtterly deceaued, and in the ſtate of condemnation, ſaue he alone, and thoſe that take part with him.</head>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:3475:39"/>
               <p> THoſe that are acquainted, with the ſhameleſnes, and boldenes of heretikes and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe perſons, doe well ynough know, that it is no new or ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge thing, to heare from them ſuche reſolute and peremptorie ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, tending to the condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of others, and the iuſtifying of them ſelues and their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked cauſes. The practiſe of former ages (as for example the <hi>Donatiſtes</hi> in <hi>Africa</hi> condemning the Churches of the people of GOD there,) and the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of latter times, as of the <hi>Anabaptiſtes</hi> in <hi>Germanie,</hi> and of the familie of loue amongeſt vs, pronounting ſharp ſentence of eternall iudgement, vpon ſuche as were not, or are not of their faction) doeth ſufficiently euince and prooue this point. So that we may ſee, with what ſpirite
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:3475:40"/>this fellowe is led, to wit, with the ſpirit of frenſey &amp; brainſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which hath carried them, &amp; him forward, to the iuſtifiyng of them ſelues in falſhood &amp; lies, &amp; to the conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning of others for ſinceritie &amp; truth. Out of which kinde of corrupt &amp; peruerſe dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, though the thing it ſelfe be euill, yet thoſe that are wiſe in God, may gather ſome profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and good inſtructions: as firſt not to beleeue all ſpirites but to try the ſame, by the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of the word, whether they be of god or no, ſeeing that there was yet neuer any, howe foulye ſoeuer they were deceiued, but that they durſt yet raſhlie and boldly, take vpon them, not only to condemne others holding co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſions, but alſo to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch their falſhoods as mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt trueths. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly, it is very
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:3475:40"/>ſtrong, to ſhewe and declare, the mightie effect of trueth it ſelfe, &amp; to teach them that doe profeſſe it with knowledge, zeale and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, to wade on in the ſame &amp; the defence of it, ſeeing the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vngodly ſo ſtiffe in the maintenance and iuſtifying of their corrupt cauſes.</p>
               <p>But to let theſe thinges paſſe for this time, and to come to the particulers y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this fellowe tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth: that Papiſtes and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie of loue, are both ſeduced, &amp; out of the way of truth, is as cleere, as the light at noone tide, and therfore that they continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their blaſphemous opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of their ſeuerall ſectes) ſhould be in the ſtate of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, none y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is enlightened with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit &amp; truth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, wil euer deny or doubte of, for (as our ſauiour ſaith) hee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth not is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned already,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:3475:41"/>becauſe hee beleeueth not in the name of the only begotten ſonne of God.</p>
               <p>Concerning Puritanes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, it is a worde of a doubtful ſignification, (before I declare my minde concerning theſe men) I will diſtinguiſh vpon it. The Nouatian Heretikes, ſo called of one <hi>Nouatus</hi> the beginner of that ſect, who held y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if a man did ſin after Baptiſme, there was no hope of repentance, were in olde time called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which is as much to ſay, as Puritans. Now if any man hold this opinion, I am ſo far of fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> allowing him in the ſame, that I feare not to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nounce (if hee liue and die in it, without beeing thorowe Gods goodnes reclaimed from it) that he is in the ſtate of exernall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, not only becauſe hee holdeth an opinion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary vnto
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:3475:41"/>the trueth of the worde of God (which ſaith; that if we haue no ſinne, wee deceiue our ſelues and the trueth is not in vs) but alſo becauſe he doeth vtterly euacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, the loue and mercie of God, which in nothing doth more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually and plainely appeare, then in the free forgiueneſſe of al our tranſgreſſions, and by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent alſo, doeth adnihillate &amp; make of no force, the merits and obedience of Chriſt, who was deliuered vp to the death, euen the death of the croſſe, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he might not onlie take away our ſinnes, but alſo aſſuredly ſeale vp in our heartes, the free pardon and full forgiueneſſe of all out tranſgreſſions whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
               <p>But for as much as this name hath byn ſlaunderouſly by that Traytor <hi>D. Saunders</hi> the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſer
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:3475:42"/>of it (as it is thought) impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; laid vpon ſome, that haue deſired the reformation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe of ſome thinges amiſſe in the Churche: and ſince by ſome other of the Papiſtes his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes being yet in induraunce, for their obſtinacie in that their hereſie, and diſobedience to her Maieſties royall authoritie, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt the ſame, for him or anie other, to giue ſuch an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Cenſure vppon them, I doubt not to pronounce it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hee or whoſoeuer they bee y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo ſhall doe, do very raſhly ruſh into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of God, to whom alone it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation, &amp; for their greate preſumption, ſhall abide horrible payne, vnleſſe it pleaſe God to giue them vnfeigned re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for the ſame.</p>
               <p>And in caſe theſe be the men he
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:3475:42"/>meaneth by the Puritans, with what equity or right, hee can charge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with theſe things, let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly iudge, yea I wil report myſelf in this cauſe, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am ſure miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like both the men, &amp; the matters y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, whether euer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were heard to affirme, either them ſelues, or theirs, to be voyd of ſinne, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any haue falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after baptiſm, there was no hope of repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance &amp; amendme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or any ſuch beaſtly and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſpeeche. If not then haue the Papiſts done euil, to cal this name fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, as it were, &amp; to giue it to ſincere Chriſtians, ſeeing that it cannot be prooued, that they held any ſuch hereſie, &amp; this felow &amp; others co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing the vſe of this name, without iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying the cauſe vpon them are found falſe witneſſe beaters.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:3475:43"/>
               <p>Concerning Proteſtants, that is to ſay, ſuche as amongeſt vs doe at this day preache and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the Goſpell, I doubte not but that in good time, they will haue an eye, to ſuch deſperate fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and cauſe him and others for their lying, to feele y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waight of a iuſt iudgement, that dare ſo boldely condemne them and the trueth, which they hold &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne. For this they muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity grow to, that ſeeing there is but one God, one faith, one Church &amp;c: and their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience telleth them, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth of this aſſertion, they muſt eyther defende that Religion that they haue already thorowe Gods goodneſſe imbraced &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed (which then they ſhal doe, when they reſiraine, the vnbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled ſpeeches of ſuche looſe and lewde fellowes more then heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:3475:43"/>they haue vſed, by ſome ſharper Cenſures and puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, either of impriſonment, baniſhment, and if need require death it ſelfe: or els yeelde vnto him and them in their corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; errors, becauſe the thing that they propounde, &amp; the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that the Goſpel deliuereth, can no more ſtand together (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng thinges directely oppoſite &amp; contrary one of them to another) then darkeneſſe &amp; light, or then hell and heauen, as hath byn al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie in ſome meaſure prooued, and more particulerly ſhalbe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared herafter. And this I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe may ſerue for a full and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient anſweare, to this lewde &amp; falſe accuſation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>12 That no outward thing (as the workes of ſanctification, vnfey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned forgiueneſſe of others, or ſuch
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:3475:44"/>like) can bee pledges, either to our ſelues or others, of our election.</head>
               <p>IT is well ſaide by one, that hee that hath once paſſed the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites &amp; boundes of modeſtie &amp; ſhamefaſtnes, muſt be indeed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſhameles. And it is as tru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſaid by an other, that error ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth alone, but that it bringeth with it, an infinit number of abſurdities &amp; corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as handmaides, to wayte vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame. How true this is, may appeare, by the lewd aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that this man hath alreadie put downe (&amp; yet by the way I muſt aduertiſe you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he foſtreth an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth more in his breſt, as perillous as any of theſe here ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed) and by the plain anſwere &amp; confutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt which his wicked concluſions, this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue now in hand, is not the leaſt euil, both becauſe it is directly againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:3475:44"/>word, &amp; alſo becauſe it fighteth againſt ſome points, that he him ſelfe holdeth.</p>
               <p>I will take the latter of theſe two &amp; purſue it firſt. This felow who would haue nothing of the threats of gods iuſtice propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, but only haue their eares filled with the ioyfull and comfortable promiſes of the word, that therby they might be aſſured of ſaluation, doth take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them not only one good teſtimony &amp; pledge of the ſame in their hearts, but many &amp; ſundry, yea and thoſe very mighty in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect For by this aſſertion, he will not admit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> either our prayers ſhould be pledges of our faith, &amp; ſo by conſequent of our ſaluation (wheras y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture, telleth vs, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not cal vpon him in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we beleeue not: &amp; againe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> who ſoeuer ſhal ral vpon the name of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:3475:45"/>the Lorde ſhalbe ſaued) or that our loue of the brethren ſhoulde be a teſtimonie of our regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and new birth, where as the woorde aſſureth vs, that by this we know, that wee are tranſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from death vnto life, becauſe wee loue the brethren: or that our vnfeigned forgiueneſſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſhould be a ſeale of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of our ſins before God, wheras our Sauiour Chriſt tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, that if wee doe forgiue men their treſpaſſes, our heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father wil alſo forgiue vs: but if wee doe not forgiue men their treſpaſſes, no more will hee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue vs our treſpaſſes. See for this purpoſe. <hi>Mat. 18 35.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to the other poynt, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſaid that it was directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the trueth of the woorde, S. Peter ſhalbe a ſufficient wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this behalf, when he ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:3475:45"/>Giue diligence to make your calling &amp; election ſure by good works, for if you doe theſe things you ſhall neuer fall: for by this meanes an entrie ſhalbee mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred vnto you abundantly, into the euerlaſting kingdome, of our Lord and ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt. The Apoſtle meaneth not heere, that our election and calling is vncertayne in reſpect of God, for we know by the truth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word that he hath written our names in the booke of life: that the gifts and graces of God, are without repentaunce: that thoſe whom hee loueth once, hee loueth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: and that there is with him no variableneſſe no not ſo much as a ſhadow of turning: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee our ſelues haue our faith ſundrie times ſore ſhaken, by the weakeneſſe of our owne corruption on the one ſide, &amp; by
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:3475:46"/>Satans continuall malice and aſſaultes on the other ſide, that therefore we ſhould what wee may (by all the graces of God, either within vs or without vs) ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt ſuch furious combats &amp; batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
               <p>I think not the contrary, but that this fellowe will make a ſhewe to ſpeake manye greate thinges, of ſpiritual feeling and comfort in Chriſt: but yet for all that, this is my iudgement co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning him, that it ſeemeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, hee knoweth not what it meaneth, becauſe it cannot be ſo much as ſuppoſed, that he hath had any ſtrong wreſtlings, with Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; his owne corruption: which may plainly appeare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he doth willingly and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly depriue himſelfe, of ſuch bigge bulwarkes &amp; mighty for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes of his faith, as this and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:3475:46"/>ſuch like are. And if this his dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, did but taint himſelfe only it were a matter of no great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance: but for as much as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the bare pretence of a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual comfort, he indeuoureth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els, but to plunge me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer heade &amp; eares in the pit of deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (for why may hee not as well depriue vs of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proppes of our faith, as the word, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes, &amp;c, as of this &amp; ſuch like) it behoueth euery one y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth his own ſaluation, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of this and al other his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent and pernicious opinions.</p>
               <p>True it is that hypocrits &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers, may in outward ſhew (as he himſelfe ſaieth) doe many good works, but yet that hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not, why that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of of God, ſhould not eyther do the like, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue ſome comfort and ſtrength therin, ſeeing God hath
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:3475:47"/>aſſured vs by his woorde that ſowe may doe. For this muſt remaine reſolut, amongeſt ſuch as loue and feare the Lord, that ſo long as wee doe vnfeignedly caſt from vs, the opinion of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite on the ſide, and faile not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the manner of doing the thing that God commaundeth vs, or in the ende, (though wee cannot doe it in that exquiſite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; perfection that the Lorde demaundeth it at our handes) yet there is no cauſe, why wee ſhoulde eyther not doe the thing at al (for that were ſinne againſt GOD in leauing vndone the thing that he requireth at our handes) neither that we ſhould bee voyde of comforte in the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the matter, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided alwaies that our reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing be not in our ſelues, neither in the thinges as they come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:3475:47"/>vs, but onely in the Lorde, and the goodnes of his grace, who hath inabled vs, pore &amp; miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wretches though we bee in ſome meaſure more or leſſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as wee haue receiued grace and aſſiſtance from him to perfourme his will.</p>
               <p>And this is that, that I would haue the children of God to imbrace, not onely as a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoiſon againſt the venomous infection of this lewd mans aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion: but as a matter of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort to their aſſaulted co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daies of their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction &amp; trial. Of which matter I wil heerafter, through Gods aſſiſtance, publiſh a treatie, that I haue alredie begunne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <head>13 That we may as wel ſay that Chriſt is fleſh of our fleſh, &amp; bone of our bones, as ſay, that wee are
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:3475:48"/>fleſhe of his fleſhe and bone of his bones.</head>
               <p>THough ſomewhat haue byn ſaid of this matter hertofore, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt &amp; ſecond articles of this treatie (and therfore we ſhal not neede heere any large diſcourſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame) yet ſomwhat I wil ſay, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; falſhood thereof may more ſenſibly appeare.</p>
               <p>Firſt therfore I affirm, that we may ſafely ſay, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wee are fleſh of of Chriſtes fleſh, &amp; bone of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bones becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture it ſelf, vſeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> faſhion &amp; manner of ſpeeche <hi>Ephe. 5.30.</hi> Whereas no ſuch grounde or warrant out of the word can be ſhewed, that he is fleſhe of our fleſhe, and bone of our bones.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very good ground of reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted vnto vs by the woorde
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:3475:48"/>of God, ſay, that we are fleſhe of his fleſh, &amp; bone of his bones, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that hee was before vs now liuing, of whom I ſuppoſe, this Libertine ſpecially ſpeaketh both in reſpect of his humanitie, which hee tooke of his mother, (when the fulneſſe of time was come) &amp; alſo in reſpect of his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal deity, by which all thinges were made, and without which, was made nothing that was made. And this mee thinketh is playnlie proued, by theſe words of the Apoſtle. <hi>Hebr. 13.8.</hi> Ieſus Chriſt yeſterday, &amp; to day, &amp; the ſame for euer. Wherfore, euen as in the very order &amp; courſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the father beeing before the childe, cannot be ſaid, to be fleſh of his childes fleſhe, and bones of his childes bones (becauſe that long ere the childe was, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father was) &amp; the latter muſt
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:3475:49"/>be denominated of the former, and not the former of the latter) ſo cannot Chriſte bee aptly and rightly ſayde, to be bones of our bones, &amp; fleſh of our fleſh, becauſe that we bee but as it were his children, and farre after him in reſpect of ſucceſſion of time. And if this were not true and ſound, that ſpeech and reaſon of Adam mentioned in <hi>Geneſis. 2.23.</hi> could not bee right, when hee ſayeth. This now is bone of my bones and fleſhe of my fleſh, ſhe ſhalbe called woman, becauſe ſhe was taken out of man. But in theſe poyntes, it is good to be wiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to ſobrietie, and to goe no further than Gods woorde will allow vs. For mine owne part, whatſoeuer I haue ſayd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in this point, I haue not done it as of curiouſnes, to carpe him, otherwiſe than the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:3475:49"/>truth I hope will beare it: and if I haue fayled (as it muſt bee confeſſed in many thinges wee offend all) I haue not done it of malice, or purpoſe, but of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance rather: and therefore I woulde haue no man to miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue my meaning, to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of any corruption, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching either the names, nature, perſon or offices of our Sauiour Chriſt. And that which I ſpeak particulerly of this pointe, I would haue to be vnderſtood, of this whole writing and of euery part and peece thereof, and of all other thinges whatſoeuer that eyther haue paſſed or ſhall paſſe from mee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="part">
               <head>14 That the worde kingdome in the ſecond petition of the Lordes prayer, is to be vnderſtood only, of the kingdome of Gods loue and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:3475:50"/>mercie, and not of his kingdome of iuſtice and power.</head>
               <p>IF his name ſhalbe raſed vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the booke of life, that taketh any thing away from the word of God, and the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it (as he that cannot lye hath moſt certainly aſſured vs of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame) then this fellowe is in a moſt daungerous and deſperate eſtate, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in the pride of his owne heart, dare bring into ſo narrow &amp; ſtraight a roome, that which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord by his eternal wiſedome, hath inlarged ſo farre.</p>
               <p>For ſeyng that the glory of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kingdome, and therfore much more of Gods kingdome (which is greater then all) conſiſteth of two parts, to wit, iuſtice &amp; iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the wicked, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour &amp; mercy towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good, and wee pray for the comming of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:3475:50"/>Gods kingdome, this fellow ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chooſe, but bee much decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that goeth about to make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſo ſcant, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> of his goodnes hath giuen vs here, ſuch a large ſtope and field to walke in. And that this may the more plainely appeare, I wil heere put downe but twoo pointes. Firſt I will ſhew, the abſurdities that enſue vpon this concluſion. Secondly, I will put downe, the true ſenſe and meaning of this petition.</p>
               <p>If this mans meaning might be accepted for currant coine, that ground &amp; principle, which hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hath beene alwaies receiued &amp; admitted, for an infallible trueth (to wit that Chriſt hath giuen vs a certayne forme, in which he hath ſhortly compriſed al points &amp; matters, that it is lawful for vs to aſke, whether they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerne God or men, or reſpect this life,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:3475:51"/>or the life to come) ſhould eaſily and with little or no doe at all, not onely be ſhaken, but caſt downe to the ground alſo. But God hath more graciouſly and liberally prouided for vs, and for the ſtrengthening of our ſayth, whileſt that it hath pleaſed him to giue vnto vs, by the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and meanes of his dearely beloued ſonn, ſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>r, though indeede very ſhort forme of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: wherein hee hath not onely manifeſted, his woonderful and vnſearchable wiſdome, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending all thinges, in ſo fewe lines or wordes: but alſo teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, his ſinguler loue, prouiding by this meanes, a moſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie help for the duines and groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our vnderſtanding, and memorie, whileſt it hath pleaſed him, in the ſame euen as it were in a little table, to deſcribe and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:3475:51"/>ſet out. whatſoeuer it is lawfull for vs to wiſh and deſire at his hunds.</p>
               <p>Beſides if wee ſhould admit this aſſertion, then this woulde follow vppon it, that when wee pray for good thinges, wee doe not demaunde or craue, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing from vs the contrary e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill thinges: and then the rule of contraries ſhoulde bee ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne alſo, and we ſhould ſee nothing in God but mercie and goodnes. Which how falſe it is may appeare by the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler both teſtimonies and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, which doe in the woord ſet out his iudgementes ſharpely threained, &amp; iuſtly executed vpon all rebellious and diſobedient people.</p>
               <p>All that know any thing out of the woord, know this to be a moſt true and infallible rule,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:3475:52"/>both in the commaundementes giuen vs by the Lorde, and in the prayer which our Sauiour hath taught vs, that as by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding good thinges, he hath forbidden vs the contrary euill thinges: &amp; as by forbidding euil thinges, he hath commaunded vs the contrary good thinges: ſo likewiſe by teaching vs to pray for the obtayning of good thinges, hee hath inſtructed vs to praye agaynſt euill thinges: &amp; by teaching vs to pray againſt euil thinges he hath taught vs to deſire at Gods handes, the contrary good thinges.</p>
               <p>To make both of theſe playne by examples. In the fifth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, when hee requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth at our handes obedience, to Magiſtrates, miniſters, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, and all others, whom it hath pleaſed the Lorde, by wit,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:3475:52"/>wealth, or any other manner of way, to prefer before vs, he hath forbidden all rebellion, diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence contempt, euil wordes, yea euil thoughts againſt the ſame perſons. And in the ſeuenth commaundement vnder adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie hee doeth not only require at our handes, to abſteyne from all filthineſſe, as whoredome, forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, adulterie, inceſt, filthie ſpeaking, vnſeemely geſtures, and all other thinges whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, which may prouoke to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe: but commaunded al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo al pureneſſe and chaſtitie, both of heart, word; &amp; behauiour. And if this were not true, there were but one way of tranſgreſſing Gods lawe, to wit, the doing of ſuch euil things as he hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden. Whereas we know by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, that this is alſo diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to God, to leaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:3475:53"/>the good thinges that hee commandeth.</p>
               <p>The like may we ſay of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. In the fourth petition vnder the name of dayly breade, the Lord doth not onely teach vs to pray for health, wealth, libertie, meate, drinke, apparell, and all other thinges whatſoeuer, that God knoweth to be meete for vs in this world, to ſuſtaine, keepe, and defend our bodies and liues by: but we pray alſo againſt all things that may tend to the hurt of our bodies &amp; liues, as hunger nakednes, ſcarſitie, peſtilence, po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uertie, bondage, and all ſuche like.</p>
               <p>So in the ſirt and laſt petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we doe not onely pray againſt faynting and falling away from God, againſt worldly vanities, fleſhly luſtes, diueliſh deceiuings &amp; ſuch like, but alſo wee pray for
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:3475:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>chriſtian patience and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in al troubles, for contempt of the world, for mortification of the fleſh, for quickening of Gods holy ſpirite in vs, and alſo for a ioyfull and glorious victorie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne, the deuil, and al try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als whaſoeuer.</p>
               <p>Now the reaſon both of the one and the other is this: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that wee cannot ſo ſoone ſpeake of the one, but the other preſently offereth it ſelfe vnto our cogitation and thought: and againe we muſt know and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that the feeling of the one in obedience without the liuely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the other by fayth, is to little or no purpoſe at all. For what woulde it profit me to al ſtaine from euill, and yet not to doe good, ſeeing that the lord requireth both the one and the other from me? Or, what ſhould
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:3475:54"/>it auaile mee, to haue euil remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from mee by prayer, and not to haue gratious &amp; good things by the ſame meanes in the name &amp; for the ſake of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt beſtowed vppon mee. Let this therfore remaine as a reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute concluſion, that this fellowe doeth euill, thus to alleadge and ſtreighten, that which the Lord hath ſo graciouſly inlarged.</p>
               <p>Moreouer vpon this there fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth another abſurdity (as this generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alwayes is very fruitefull, procreating and beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting infinite children like vnto it ſelfe) and that is this: that if Gods kingdome comprehende nothing but mercy and loue, and that there is no iuſtice in this place to be founde, that then his kingdom, ſhal not be ſo large as earthly kingdomes are, who are ordeined of GOD himſelfe, to
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:3475:54"/>mainteine the good, &amp; to puniſh the euil: &amp; by a conſequent, that there are no wicked men, vppon who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that part of his kingdome, which conſiſteth of iuſtice and iudgement, ſhould be executed: &amp; by another conſequent that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, this Libertine ſhould be found co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who ſaid before in the <hi>11.</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, that al that were not of his profeſſion, were vtterly deceiued and in the ſtate of condemnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And then another error woulde flow from hence, that as <hi>Origen</hi> dreamed, both Diuelles and all men ſhould be ſaued in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Turke, Iewe, Papiſt and all, which howe falſe it is, hath byn in part declared before.</p>
               <p>By this you may ſee, what an of ſpring and generation there is of hereſy &amp; corruption, &amp; what a worlde or ſea of abſurdities, ſuch
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:3475:55"/>groſſe opinions bring with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Let euery one of vs ſeeing theſe great miſchiefes and inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, be learned and warned thereby, to withſtand the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of euil, and to ſtick faſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to that with ſoundnes &amp; ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of truth, that God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed vnto vs in his woorde, caſting farre from vs, the ydle inuentions, and wicked deuiſes of our owne heades, knowing that ſuch imaginations, are not onely great defamings to Gods glorie, but foule corruptions, yea great condemnation to our own ſoule.</p>
               <p>Now ſomewhat concerning the true meaning of this petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo an end for this pointe, And though herein I might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre my ſelfe, to that which I haue written heretofore expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the lordes prayer, in a little
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:3475:55"/>treatiſe that I did write of ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie meditations, yet becauſe occaſion is here offered, to ſpeak ſomewhat largely, and by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding of one petition, light may be giuen to another, I will with the good leaue and liking of the godly reader, in as fewe words as I can diſcourſe ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what concerning this point.</p>
               <p>We know by the trueth and light of Gods worde, that Gods gouernment ſtretcheth it ſelfe, farre and wide ouer all, ſo that there is no creature, neither in heauen nor in earth, nor in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces vnder the earth, but either willingly or vnwillingly (as you would ſay) it muſt of neceſſitie be ſubiecte to this his moſte ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne &amp; high power. And this we may cal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> generall iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or gouernement that GOD exerciſeth ouer all, from which
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:3475:56"/>no creatures, no not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuels or wicked men (though he doe not rule them or guide them by his holy ſpirite) can bee exempted, though they gladly wiſhe and deſire the ſame.</p>
               <p>We know further by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth &amp; light of the ſame word, that as earthly kings &amp; princes, haue in ſeueral quarters &amp; parts of their dominions, many thouſandes of their ſubiectes, all which make but one body: ſo the Lorde hath ſome in heauen, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we call the church triumphant, (becauſe in the victorie &amp; conqueſt of Chriſt, they do alredy in ſoule, triumph ouer ſinne &amp; hell, and ſome here in earth, which we cal y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church millitant, who thorow the grace &amp; ſtrength, that God be ſtoweth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, doe battle as againſt corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in others, ſo ſpecially againſt ſinne in themſelues.</p>
               <p>But as there is no earthly
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:3475:56"/>kingdom, though it comprehend all the people of the ſame, vnder the name &amp; title of ſubiectes, but it hath notwithſtanding, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly many factious and ſeditious perſons therein, but counterfeite ſubiectes alſo, vppon which the prince and magiſtrate, wil in the day of the manifeſtation of their tranſgreſſion, take iuſt ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce, according to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall tranſgreſſions: ſo the Churche, heere cannot bee ſo purged (though it pleaſe God manie times, by exerciſing his iudgementes, to ſhe we his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice agaynſt wicked hypocrites and rebellious perſons) but that ſome chaffe will reinayne with the wheate: And yet when the day of wynowing ſhal come, then ſhall the good corne, bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued into the Lords gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, &amp; the chaffe ſhalbee burned with
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:3475:57"/>vnquenchable fire. Al this ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not onely to ſhewe what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblaunce there is betweene earthly princes gouernmentes, and Gods: but alſo to proue, that this ſpirituall kingdome of God conſiſteth chiefly in twoo pointes. One is, that he beare rule ouer a readie, willing and vnfeined hearted people, as it is ſayde in <hi>Pſalm. 110.3.</hi> the other is that he confound his aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in their boldnes and pride.</p>
               <p>So that in this petition, wee demaund theſe twoo thinges, Gods mercie towardes his elect and his iudgement and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation vpon the wicked of what ſort ſoeuer they be. For as we cannot deſire the cleare light of truth, but that we doe withall wiſh the remoouing, of darknes and ignorance, ſo we cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire God to guide his faythfull
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:3475:57"/>people by his ſpirit, but wee doe on the other ſede deſire him to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer throw and confound, al thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do obſtinately withſtand his holy will, and proudly lift vp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues againſt him, at no hande ſuffring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be brought in obedience and ſubiection to his bleſſed gouernement, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer contrary ſhewe many of them will notwithſtanding pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend.</p>
               <p>If any man woulde thinke this to be againſt charitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to may for all men. I anſwere that this is no whirte at all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. For we muſt not mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure tharitie by the line of our owne reaſon, but by that figure or rule that God who is in him ſelfe the God of charitie, hath ſanctified and ſet foorth vnto vs in his woord, and there we ſhall
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:3475:58"/>find, that though we be comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to praye for aſt men general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (that is for al ſorts &amp; degrees of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as magiſtrates, miniſters, men, women, young, old, &amp; that this is enioyned vs, becauſe wee certeinly know not, who beſides our ſelues euery one of vs in par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticular are elected &amp; reprobate) that yet if it bee graunted in the bare letter, it vtterly ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Gods eternall reprobation, who in his iuſtice hath ordained many to be veſſels of his wrath, as in his grace hath appou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed ſome to bee veſſels of mercy, &amp; is directly contrary, to ſuch pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers as Chriſt himſelfe the ſunne of GOD, Saint Paule and other holy men haue made as may appeare. <hi>Iohn. 17.9. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians 5.12. 1. Iohn. 5.16.</hi> and ſundry ſuch other places, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:3475:58"/>for auoiding of tediouſnes I remit the reader.</p>
               <p>To conclude, becauſe I feare, I haue beene ouerlong in this point, this I take to be the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this petition, that for as much as Gods kingdome is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ouer good &amp; bad (though the wicked indeede, cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be ſaide to be his ſubiects) and that hee is glorified both in the deſtruction of the wicked, and alſo in the ſaluation of the elect: wee praye therefore that hee woulde ouerthrowe the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked generally, and namely, and particularly Hypocrites, who are not ſincerely ſubiecte to his kingdome and gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though they woulde ſeeme ſo to be and that on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, he would gouerne his choſen ones, as outwardly in
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:3475:59"/>his church, by the ſcepter of his owne word and diſcipline, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly in their conſciences, by the gratious working of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit, mortifying in them dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more and more, the luſtes and concupiſcences of their owne heartes, till hee haue brought them thorow the vale of their pilgrimage, for euer to triumph with Ieſus Chriſt, their captain and leader, and withal the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and glorious companie of heauen, continually to praiſe his moſt holy name.</p>
               <p>Whereupon I conclude, that if the meaning of our Sauiour Chriſt in this petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be ſo large as it is indeede, and I hope, hath been hitherto plainely and plentifully prooued, all that loue the Lorde Ieſus Chriſt to their immortalitie, will abhorre
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:3475:59"/>and that from the bottome of good heartes, ſuch preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirites, as in the pride of their vnderſtanding, will with this excluſiue particle onely, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine that, that God hath gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly enlarged, ſpecially ſeeing the purpoſe of our Sauiour was not onely to ſet foorth God his fathers mercie, but alſo his iuſtice, who in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fulnes of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that was in him, (foreſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well inough the relaption of mans harte who if he hearde of nothing but mercie, would wax careleſſe, and if he hearde of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but iuſtice, would be caſt downe aboue meaſure) did ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt wiſely temper ſweete thinges and ſower thinges to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, to the ende, that by his goodneſſe the godly might bee comforted, and by his inſtice the wicked might be terrified, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:3475:60"/>vs as it were by his exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to deale ſo, and not vtterly to aboliſh out of mens heartes the feare of God (which ariſeth in ſome ſorte, of a ſenſible feeling of his iuſtice and iudgementes) as this Libertine woulde haue vs to doe. See before Article <hi>11.</hi> and in other places.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="part">
               <head>15 That Chriſt did not fully fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh our redemption vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe but that he ſuffered ſomewhat after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde. ſe pag. 40. to 56.</head>
               <p>THis ſpeeche hee vttered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt many other abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as a ground of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his groſſe opinion, concerning Chriſt his diſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t into hel, of which we haue ſpoken before, in the eyght Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle.</p>
               <p>The vntruth of this his aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion appeareth, in that it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:3475:60"/>vnto the wordes of Chriſt himſelfe, when he ſaid, <hi>[It is fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed,]</hi> meaning therby that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and ſaluation of al the beleeuers; was now accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in that ſame one and only ſacrifice, which then hee offered and not as this fellowe imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth and expoundeth it, that the malice and enuy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes towards Chriſt, was then at an ende, when they had cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied him. For beſides, that this his ſpeech, is a meere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture, without any ſhewe eyther of woordes or circumſtaunces ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the Scriptures, it is flatly and directly contrary, to that which is expreſſed by S. <hi>Matthew</hi> in the ſeuen and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Chap. where after his death they declared their malice tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards him, one while in words as whileſt they called him deceauer
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:3475:61" rendition="simple:additions"/>and an other while by deeds as whileſt they went about, by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their watch, to keepe him downe, frome riſing agayne.</p>
               <p>And yet in the. <hi>28.</hi> chapter of that Goſpell, their malice doeth more plainely appeare, in that they went about to conceale and deface the trueth of his riſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, partly by bribing the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers that wacht the ſepulchre, partly by deuiſing a moſt falſe lie, ſaying y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his diſciples had ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len him away by night: &amp; part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by ſpreding and conueghing the ſayd falſhod ouer as it were by tradition, to their poſteritie, the people of the Iewes.</p>
               <p>Moreouer it is flatly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectlye contrarye to the plaine woordes of the Apoſtle. <hi>Col. 2.14.15.</hi> ſaying that Chriſte euen vpon the croſſe, did put out the hande writing of ordenaunces
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:3475:61"/>that was agaynſt vs, whiche was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary vnto vs, which alſo he tooke out of the way, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened vpon the croſſe, and hath ſpoyled the principalities &amp; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and hath made a ſhewe of them openly, and hath trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed ouer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſame croſſe meaning thereby that Chriſte hath ſet vs free by his ſuffrings on the croſſe, not onely from all the figures and ceremonies of the lawe (which tended ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to theſe twoo endes: to witte to declare firſt, the great corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that was in vs, &amp; the great condemnation, that by the ſame wee deſerued: as for example, the cutting, away of the foreſkin, and the vſuall waſhings, to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the outwarde filthineſſe of mans corrupt nature: the kyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of beaſtes for ſacrifice, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that we our ſelues, had
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:3475:62"/>deſerued death, yea euen eternall death: and ſecondly to repreſent Chriſt, his death &amp; bleſſed obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, who was indeede figured likewiſe by the ſame) but alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the power of Sathan, of whom wee were helde captiues at his pleaſure. So that now Chriſt hauing yeelded that Sacrifice and obedience for vs, neyther ſinne nor Sathan, nor the lawe nor condemnation are able to laye anye thing to the charge of Gods choſen, ſeeing God is on their ſide, who ſpared not his owne ſonne, but gaue him for them all to death, euen to the death of the Croſſe, that ſo hee might reconcile all beleeuers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Beſides, ſeeing that the word, <hi>[redemption]</hi> doth properly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte the freeyng of ſome one or other, from the power of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:3475:62"/>that kept the ſame parties in captiuitie and bondage, and this was vſually perfourmed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the price or rate ſet, for their redemption &amp; libertie was ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied &amp; payd: &amp; ſeeing wee know, that as we were vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e of the Diuel &amp; eternal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by meanes of our ſinnes: ſo we were deliuered by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> price of our redemption, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, in whom it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God, to reconcile the worlde vnto himſelf, while he made him that knew no ſinne to bee made ſinne for vs, that is to ſay, a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice &amp; price for ſinne: &amp; ſeeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> this Sacrifice or price was not performed &amp; payd but by offring vp of himſelf once for al, vpon the Altar of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, we cannot ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be otherwiſe perſwaded but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath fully redeemed vs, by this only &amp; ſufficient ſacrifice.</p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:3475:63"/>
               <p> Indeed we confeſſe, and muſt of neceſſitie confeſſe it, becauſe it is the trueth of the Lorde, that ſometimes this woord <hi>[redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion]</hi> as alſo this word <hi>[death of Chriſt]</hi> is vſed in ſcripture, not only for the price of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the ſuffrings of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, but for all the fruites and effectes, that at his death, and after his death he perfourmed, or doth perfourme in the behalf of his elect: As his reſurrection aſcention, interceſſion and ſuch like. But yet, when the woorde thus ſpeaketh (as it vſeth not theſe kindes of ſpeeches with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great reaſon) to wit, becauſe Chriſtes death, reſurrection, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention, &amp;c. cannot bee deuided (for to what ende ſhould it profit vs to knowe that Chriſte were dead, if he roſe not againe? and what ſhould his reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:3475:63"/>vs, if hee were not aſcended? And in what ſteed could his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention ſtande vs, if hee did not thereby, fulfill the office of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall mediator between God and his people?) ſo it doeth no whit at all confirme thereby ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this or any other abſurd aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, that this or any other ſuch phantaſticall ſpirite ſhall blow abrode: But putting apart for the whole, which is a matter very vſuall in the ſcripture, hee doeth by the part vnderſtand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole, &amp; by that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goeth before, meane that alſo which foloweth after. Which kinde of interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ſenſe, this fellowe will at no hand accept or allow of. And yet this notwithſtanding wee ſhall ſee that theſe thinges are ſeuerally mentioned alſo in the newe Teſtament. Let one place or to ſerue for many, As <hi>Rom. 4.
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:3475:64"/>25.</hi> It is ſaide that Chriſt was deliuered to death for our ſins and is riſen againe for our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Alſo <hi>Rom. 8.34.</hi> It is ſaid that Chriſt is he which is dead, yea or rather which is riſen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Who is alſo at the right hande of GOD, and maketh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt alſo for vs. The holy Ghoſt giuing vs thereby to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, both when he ſpeaketh general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; alſo whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſpeketh particu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>larly, that we ſhoulde learne to looke for, both the whole, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery parte and peece of our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and ſanctification, in the perſon of his ſonne and not in our ſelues at any hand: and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vs alſo further, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we knowe that ſinne, hath not onely hindered the courſe of Gods mercies towardes vs, but let in vpon vs withall the floodes of his iuſtice, ſeeing we beleeue alſo that Chrſtes righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:3475:64"/>to our comfort co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth of <hi>2.</hi> parts, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, the taking away of our ſinnes, &amp; the clothing of vs with his righteouſneſſe, &amp; inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende that therby we may ſtand with boldnes &amp; puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of God, &amp; ſeeing al this is brought to paſſe by his death &amp; reſurrection, we ſhoulde therfore both generally &amp; parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culerly looke into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde for our inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, &amp; not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; iumble them together as this fellowe doeth for the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of erroneous and abſurd opinions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="part">
               <head>16. That the laſt woordes that Chriſt ſpake vpon the croſſe, were theſe, My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me.</head>
               <p>Though it bee a matter of no greate importaunce in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte of it ſelfe, toe knowe
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:3475:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>which were the firſt or whiche were the laſt woordes that our ſauiour vttered vppon the croſſe yet becauſe, that theſe woordes fight againſt the truth of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie as it is put downe by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts and were alleadged by this fellow, to improoue the true expoſition of theſe woords. <hi>It is finiſhed,</hi> handled in the, <hi>15.</hi> article ſome what in fewe words ſhalbe ſaid of the ſame.</p>
               <p>By comparing the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtes <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> who do at large ſet out, the hiſtorie of Chriſtes death and ſuffering the one in the. <hi>26.</hi> chapter of his goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, &amp; the other in the. <hi>19.</hi> it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that Chriſt, after that he with a loud voyce had cryed ſaying, <hi>Ely Ely Lamaſabatany,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, <hi>My God, my God, why haſte thou forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me:</hi> and after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they had taken a ſponge and fuled it
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:3475:65"/>with viniger, and Ieſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe had receiued of it: he cryed againe with a loud voyce, as <hi>Matthew</hi> reporteth it verſe. <hi>50.</hi> not erpreſſing what wordes hee vſed in that cry, but yet <hi>Luke</hi> in his <hi>23.</hi> chapt. ver. <hi>46.</hi> ſaith he vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered theſe woordes, <hi>Father into thy handes I commend my ſpirite.</hi> and <hi>Iohn.</hi> chapter. <hi>19.</hi> verſe. <hi>30.</hi> ſayth, he ſayd, <hi>It is finiſhed.</hi> By which places it appeareth that our Sauiour Chriſte vttered both theſe ſpeeches laſt vpon the croſſe, and not the other which he affirmeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="part">
               <head>17 That all the Iewes general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhould be called to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Reſt perſwaded that this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, ſauoureth, (as many of the other doe) of the ydle una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:3475:66"/>and dotage of his own hearte &amp; braine, becauſe no ſuch thing can be reſolutely &amp; certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded, either by the playne words of the holy ſcripture or by any circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance thereof, for mine owne part, this is that, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am perſwaded, that all Chriſtians may ſafely hold concerning this doubtful &amp; intricate queſtion, to wit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> foraſmuch as the ſcripture in many reſpects, make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewe and Gentil equal as appeareth. <hi>Rom. 3.9. Rom. 10.12. Rom. 11.32.</hi> and in manie other places: &amp; we know by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of ſaluation, was general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offered to al the Gentiles, and yet all receiued it not: naye which is more, amongſt thoſe which gaue heeretofore, and giue at this day, an outwarde conſent, to the doctrine taught, many are caſtawaies, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:3475:66"/>we may ſafely conclude, that though the Lords truth, ſhould bee generally reuealed, to all the Iewes, yet al the Iewes, ſhuld not haue an effectuall calling, &amp; by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequent, ſhould not be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſtored, to the hope and fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of eternal life.</p>
               <p>For if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were true, then ſhoulde the Iew not in many outwarde things only, but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hope &amp; poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of better things, be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before the Gentiles, which I ſuppoſe no man in the world wil euer be able to iuſtifie.</p>
               <p>He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil goe beyond this, may be wiſe in his own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceipt, &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh away whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath done, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> idle imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; dotage of his owne heart. Wherefore it ſhalbe good, to put a ſtay heere in time, and in this and ſuch like points to lette goe the curiouſneſſe of our owne heades, wading no further therein; then the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueled
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:3475:67"/>wil of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, hath ſet out: whiche hee hath manifeſted to this end, that we &amp; our poſterity might knowe, beleeue and doe the ſame, ſtaying our ſelues and our wiſedomes in the obedience of that onely, and not to ſearche beyond it, leaſt we be ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of his glorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="part">
               <head>18 That the word [Sacrament] is not to be found in the ſcripture, and therefore not to be vſed, but the woorde [Record.]</head>
               <p>IF queſtion were of woords on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not of matters alſo, wee woulde eaſily graunte the firſte parte of this aſſertion, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is true in the letter, though alleaged to a falſe ende: and alſo becauſe the Apoſtle re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth vs, that we ſhould not ſtriue about woordes, which is
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:3475:67"/>to no profit, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peruerting of the hearers. But foraſmuch as this ſpeech carrieth with it ſome dangerous conſequences, it ſhall bee good for vs, to looke ſomewhat into it.</p>
               <p>True it is that S. Peter ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any man ſpeake, hee ſhoulde ſpeake as the woordes of God: yet this hindereth not but that we may without danger of ſinn and offence, vſe ſuch woordes as we finde not in the ſcriptures: if ſo be that the woordes bee not, eyther in them ſelues, or in the ende wherunto they are ſpoken, contrary to godlines and hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie: ſpecially then, when, though we haue not the woordes them ſelues in the Scriptures, yet we haue others of the ſelf ſame ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, and the matter alſo it ſelfé that thoſe woordes import, compriſed in the holie Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:3475:68"/>
               <p> To deale eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler word <hi>Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> I find it, to be of double vſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is vſed in the law, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is put, for a pledge, of ſome bargaine, couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dfaſting, Now why we ſhoulde not vſe if, ſeeing that the Lord hath ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſacraments, to be ſeales and pledges of his mercy towardes vs, &amp; of the couenauntes that in the ſame mercy hee hath made with vs, I can ſee no reaſon vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we would goe about (as I ſuppoſe this fellowe ſhooteth at this marke) to fruſtrate and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue our ſelues, as of termes &amp; words, that doe very ſignificant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſet out vnto vs holy things, ſo of the holy thinges themſelues. Sometimes it is vſed in milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie arte, &amp; then it is put for a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne profeſſion or othe as if
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:3475:68"/>were, that captaines &amp; generals of armies, ordeined, to lay vpon ſouldiers, thereby the better to keepe them (after that they were choſen to the roomes and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſouldiers) in the faithfull obſeruation and perſormance of ſuch points as they in duety did owe to the common wealth and prince who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſerued. And this kind of promiſe or othe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued &amp; that in preſcript words was cal led a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, becauſe they did vſe for the ratification &amp; confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of it, certayne holie thinges as they ſuppoſed.</p>
               <p>Now, ſeeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, euen for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tying of our fayth more faſt vnto him, hath ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation thereof, hath annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, certaine holy things therun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, ſuch as the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are in the ſacraments, which are holy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are appointed to holie
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:3475:69"/>ends &amp; vſes as before hath been ſhewed article. <hi>5.</hi> Why ſhoulde not wee, vſe ſuch woordes, as may liuely and ſenſiblie inſtruct vs, in the truth of thoſe thinges though that the ſcriptures vſe not the ſame words.</p>
               <p>For mine owne part, I ſee no reaſon, why we may not for lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning ſake, vſe ſome words not in vſe in the woorde, ſo that we do it not without ſome good cauſe, nor innouate or change anye thing, from the doctrine of the Apoſtles and prophets.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, ſeeing wee haue woordes of the like ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as ſigne, pledge, ſeale, (and as this felow him ſelf alſo confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth) Recorde: there is no reaſon why wee ſhoulde abſtaine from the vſe of that woorde, which, though it differ in ſounde from the reſt, yet doeth it in ſubſtance
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:3475:69"/>and effect, agree very well with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; expreſſeth the ſame things that they doe.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, if this mans rule were true, wee ſhoulde not vſe the woord trinitie, nor many other wordes that our chriſtian religion embraceth, becauſe wee haue not that woorde in vſe in the ſcripture. But leauing this man in his dotage, wee doe and may very well and ſafely vſe it, becauſe that though wee finde not the woord there, yet we find the matter by the woorde ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied there. It is much to be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, leſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnder this large &amp; loſe concluſion, this fellowe, woulde firſt in ſome dangerous opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons heretofore ſette abroche by <hi>Seruetus</hi> and others: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I would wiſh all chriſtians to take heede of ſuch ſlye, ſubtile, and corrupt ſpeeches.</p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:3475:70"/>
               <p> To al this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hitherto I haue put down, I haue thought good to adde this cautio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that as my meaning is not, to improue any, in the vſe of any lawfull woord, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conditions that I haue before expreſſed: ſo it is not my mind, to approue or allow any, in the vſe of ſtraunge and affected termes, vnder which heretikes of all times, haue cuſtomably ſhrowded themſelues, &amp; in which faculty y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heretikes of our daies, ſpecially, &amp; particularly the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of loue, are very pregnant, &amp; plentifull, as to euery one but meanely acquainted with there bookes, doth plainly appeare.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="part">
               <head>19 That there wil come a time, wherin there ſhalbe no neede of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments in this life: his reaſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there wil be ſuch multitudes
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:3475:70"/>conuerted, that there ſhalbe no ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to miniſter the ſacraments vnto them.</head>
               <p>WHat ground he ſhould haue for this aſſertion, I thinke no man of ſounde iudgement can well perceaue. Sure I am that the ſcripture, doeth in ſundry places both by examples and teſtimonies, conclude the contrary. Take one place for al. The Apoſtle Saint Paule, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, that the Lorde ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the ſacrament of his ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to put vs in remembrance of him, and of the graces that wee reape and receaue by him, euen vntill his comminge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne in the cloudes with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and great glorie, to iudge the quicke and the dead. This fellow mindeth (as it ſhould ſeeme) by
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:3475:71"/>vttering this concluſion, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make void this plain place of Saint Paul, but to robbe vs as of the ſigne that ſhoulde put vs in minde of Chriſts remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce, ſo of the remembrance of Chriſt himſelfe, and of the gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces that in him and by him are dayly beſtowed vpon vs. For of neceſſitie, one of theſe twoo things muſt needes followe, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that this mans aſſertion is true, which no godly man I ſuppoſe will euer conſent vnto, &amp; Paul (his writing is vnſound which bee it farre from any to thinke, muche more for anye to ſpeake, and vtter) or elſe Paules ſpeech muſt be true &amp; his falſe, which I am ſure all of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding will eaſily confeſſe: and the reaſon hereof is, becauſe that the one of them are as directly contrary to the other, as light &amp;
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:3475:71"/>darkenes truth and falſhood.</p>
               <p>Now out of this I infer fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that if the Lordes ſupper it ſelfe, be perpetual and muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in the church of God, how fewe or howe many ſoeuer the members therof be: then the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of baptiſme, hauing the ſame inſtitutor, that the other hath, to witte Chriſt Ieſus, and being ordeined for the ſame end, that is for the ſtrengthening of our fayth in the truth of Gods promiſes: and for the ſame peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that is, for all thoſe, that are gathered into the compaſſe and booſome of Gods Church muſt likewiſe bee perpetuall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure vnto the end of the world in the Church howſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes thereof increaſe.</p>
               <p>And foraſmuche as wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg no more ſacraments in the Church of God, but theſe
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:3475:72"/>two, and it hath byn before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that theſe two ſhalbe perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, it followeth ther vpon, that there ſhalbe no ſuch time in this life as this man dreameth of, wherein there ſhalbee no vſe or neede of the ſacramentes. As for the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that he addeth, I take it to be ſo farre of from hauing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny force in it, that it is nothing, but a cunning or fine colour or myſt rather caſt before mens eies to darken them from beholding an Anabaptiſticall concluſion, who hold, that men may atteine to ſuche perfection in this life (which thing alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> family doth ſtiffely vrge) that they ſhall not ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in need of the word &amp; ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. It is a ſtrange aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to ſay, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude of ſuche as ſhould be conuerted, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dead idols to the liuing God, ſhoulde hinder the adminiſtration of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:3475:72"/>which God himſelfe hath ordeined for their good. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like this fellow ſuppoſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h, either that the Lord did not foreknow the number of thoſe, that ſhoulde be called into his Church, or elſe were not able ſufficiently to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide, that thoſe, that doe apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine vnto him might haue their liueries and cogniſaunces, wher by they might be knowen to bee his ſeruauntes, both of which or either of which to think, were intollerable blaſphemie.</p>
               <p>Beſide we know, by the truth of Gods holy word, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer this fellow dreameth of multitudes to be conuerted, yet the number of thoſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhalbe out of the boſome of the church, ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be greater, by muche, then thoſe that ſhalbe gathered, into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſocietie and fellowſhippe
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:3475:73"/>thereof. And yet amongſt them many alſo ſhalbe caſt away. So that vnleſſe all the worlde, or the greateſt parte there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhould be conuerted vnto God (which I am ſure neither this fellow nor any for him will euer bee able to proue wee neede not feare, that either multitudes ſhould hinder the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſacraments, or that leiſure ſhould not bee ſufficient for the ſame, and yet though either the one or the other could be proued, what are wee, that wee ſhoulde diſpenſe vtterly to leaue of, the inſtitution and order of GOD: nay rather, it were the duetie of euery good man, that ſeeing hee cannot doe all that the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, yet he ſhould do that that the Lorde inableth him to performe, for otherwiſe wee might eaſily caſt from vs the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:3475:73"/>whole yoke of the Law of God, becauſe we are not able i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>deed, wholy to fulfill it though tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the goodnes and aſſiſtance of our God, we walke nowe and then in the performance of ſome parte and peece thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="part">
               <head>20. That it is hypocriſie for one chriſtian to reproone an other for ſwearing, or any ſuch other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, which he calleth but trifles.</head>
               <p>If this fellowe had ſayde, that many men in reprouing others doe fall into the ſinne of hypecri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, pride, or ſuch like, whileſt that they would ſeeme in re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ing of others to bee better than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or to loath that in others, which perhaps inwardly they foſter and feede in them ſelues, he had ſpoken the truth, becauſe it is a fault, that men may not
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:3475:74"/>only be eaſily ouer taken withal, but ſundry times indeed ſall into the ſame, ſeeking thereby their owne credite and praiſe. But for a man to condemne any good thing (as this fellow ſeemeth to doe) for the euill or corruption of the partie that intermedleth therein, it argueth follie more then palpable. Firſt becauſe thinges of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues good, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they may bee prophaned by wicked men, cannot of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and in their owne nature become euill. Secondly, becauſe if that were true, wee might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily condemne as thinges euill and vnlawfull, both the worde and ſacramentes, ſpecially if they were preached and adminiſtred vnto vs by euill miniſters, or wicked men made a ſhewe to receiue them, whiche ſauoureth
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:3475:74"/>ſtrongly of Donat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſtrie. But whether d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not this mans arrogancie and impudencie driue him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Marke I beſeeche you howe by this ſpeeche hee dares make GOD the Author of euill: to wit of hypocrifie. For GOD demaundeth this duetie of vs, that wee ſhoulde haue an eye one ouer an other for good, and that in the ſpirite of mildneſſe and brotherly loue, wee ſhould friendly admoniſhe and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly repro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue one another. To this ende is it ſaide in <hi>Leuiticus.</hi> Thou ſhalt not hate thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in thy hearte, but thou ſhalt plainely rebuke thy neighbour, and ſuffer not ſinne vpon him. Our Sauiour Chriſte alſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs to tell our brother his
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:3475:75"/>fault, and y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> this fellow dares, ſay, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pocrifie ſo walke in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>edie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of theſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, It this be not to charge God with euil, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et al men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>idge, and if this bee not the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w of Gods law, &amp; word I know not what is: But this fellow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aieth not here, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>eth to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vtter as great and groſſe blaſphemies calling ſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing and other tranſgreſſions of the firſt and ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d table, but tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s, Be l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke this fellow is new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly godded with God (as the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milians ſay) or elſe he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> take vpon him thus Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, to diſpenſe with the holy commandements. If hee that breaketh one of the leaſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements and teacheth men ſo, ſhalbe caſt into vtter darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, what ſhal become of this fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:3475:75"/>that feareth not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſome of the greateſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> men to do the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ating of ſinne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> perſon pract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame little or no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otion. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> it differeth not much from the Stoickes opi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſinne equ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e reſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> by the truth of Gods woord, that not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aue is. more gres nous that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and man (which may<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ainely appeare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: by the orde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that God himſelfe ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>eth in propo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ding his law in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> tables) but alſo that euen one and the ſelfe ſame ſinne, may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> aggrauated and made mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous by the circumſtances, of time, pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, perſon, and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ner of doing. So farre of are wee therefore from accounting the greateſt ſins trifles, as this fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:3475:76"/>doeth, that wee counce the leaſt offence that can bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt Gods lawe, by thought, word, or deede, to be of and in it ſelfe, without Gods great mercie pardoning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, a meane to pull vpon vs eternal death and condemnation, which argueth that the thing it ſelfe committed, muſt of neceſſity bee a greater matter by much, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a trifle, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls GOD as a very ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous &amp; vniuſt GOD, that for trifles and matters of no importaunce, layeth ſo ſore is iudgement vpon the world. But for this matter I ſaie, let God bee iuſt when hee ſpeaketh, and pure when hee iudgeth. And as for this Lioertine, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pexnicious Heretikes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, let them receiue that whiche is due vnto them to wit,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:3475:76"/>ſhame &amp; confuſion of face before God and good men.</p>
               <p>One thing more out of this laſt poynte and ſo an ende. I ſee in this inſtrument of Sathan, a liuely image and picture as it were of his Diueliſhe corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. They that are acquainted with the ſuggeſtions of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, knowe, that al his aſſaultes doe at all times and in all thinges, tende euer to extremitie. For example, if hee cannot drawe men to idolatrie, he will labour to bringe them to contempt of true religion: Agayne, if he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not preuayle to make men coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, he will aſſay by al meanes poſſible to drawe them to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digallitie and waſtfulneſſe, ſo harde a thing is it, too keepe &amp; directe and righte courſe ſayling in this worlde of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:3475:77"/>wherein we are toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp and downe with the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous waues of our owne corruption and Sathans ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, betweene theſe twoo moſt dangerous gulfes and huge rockes. The ſelfe ſame thing, doth this felow, ledde no doubt, by the ſpirit of ſathan, propound and practiſe in this place. For ſeeing that hee cannot carrie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way men, into a eurious behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of other mens tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and therby into a forgetful nes of their owne, hee doeth lar bour by this his ſpeece, to make them vtterly to neglect that great dutie of brotherly admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and reproofe, which both God and chriſtian charitie doth require at their hands. And fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that in the vglye ſight of ſinne, hee cannot terrifie mens conſciences to deſpayre, hee ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoreth,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:3475:77"/>by debaſing bey onde all right and reaſon, ſinne it ſelfe &amp; the miſerable effectes and fruits thereof, to make men voyde of al remorſe &amp; conſcience of the ſame, the greateſt inſtrument &amp; meane y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sathan doth vſe to indurate and harden mens heartes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Thoſe that are taught of god haue learned by the light of his woord and woorking of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, not onely to take heede of ſuch dangerous and deſperate extremities but alſo in all holy obedience to God, and dutifull loue to their brethren, rightly ſo to deuide the times, that they will haue a ſeaſon, wherein to looke to them ſelues, and thoſe thinges, that be amiſſe in them, labouring according to the n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of grace receiued, the a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof: and alſo another time wherein they will by the
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:3475:78"/>ſpirite of loue and gentleneſſe labour what in them lieth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of their brethren A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, becauſe they knowe, that mans iudgement is bleared, if not altogether defaced, thorowe ſinne and tranſgreſſion, manie times calling good, euill, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, good: and beſide, being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to themſelues in their owne cauſes, often iuſtifying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in thoſe thinges, wherein they ſhuld condemne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, they doe vſe to meaſure out ſinne by an other line, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnderſtanding of their own heartes: that is, by the trueth &amp; touchſtone of the word, which is able not only to inſtruct them to put a difference betweene good and euill, but euen betweene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil and euil, and good and good. For by the trueth of that worde they knowe, that there is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:3475:78"/>and degrees both in the one and in the other. And that this is trueth, it is as cleere, as the light at noone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ide. There re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth no more but this, to know and beleeue for our incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in well doyng, that as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as walke, according to this rule, ſhal haue peace vpon them, and mexcie, &amp; the like ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be powred foorth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon al the Iſrael of God. (:)</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="156" facs="tcp:3475:79"/>
            <head>¶ An aduertiſement to the <hi>Godly Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SInce the printing of this work was attempted, certain rumors haue bin ſpread abrode, by this lewd Libertine, or ſome of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourers, that he neuer held or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded many of theſe or ſuch like propoſitions. For mine owne parte I thought good, to aduertiſe the (ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reader) of the falſhood of this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, &amp; that not onely vpon mine owne knowledge, (though therein I might haue ſayd much, as who hath bin this 9. or. 10. yeeres ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what acquainted, with theſe &amp; ſuch like curſed concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of his: as that we need not to pray ſpecially for forgiuenes of ſinnes: and that if we keepe our ſelues in our caſtle Chriſt nothing that we can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit in this fleſh, can be ſinne vnto vs: and that
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:3475:79"/>now ſith we are maried to Chriſt, there are no more me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> becauſe al are become women) but vpon the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red teſtimonies alſo, of good and ſufficient witneſſes, in whoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring &amp; in mine likewiſe he did not many moneths ſince, ſhameleſly vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; ſpeake, the matters and points before rehearſed. Yea if the beaſtly bookes that he hath penned, as one which he calleth his muſicke, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which he calleth his axe, and ſuch others might be brought to light, the world ſhould then ſee, not onely theſe, but euen a whole ſea of ſuch like abſurdities and falſhoods, broched and ſpread abrode. So that there is no reaſon why the chriſtian reader, ſhould beleue, ſuch flying re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portes publiſhed, verie cunninglie, to the diſcredit eyther of this, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other thing, that may be ſet out againſt him, ſpecially, conſidering that it is Satans common cuſtome,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:3475:80"/>both in himſelf, and in his ſeruants, to colour their wickednes with ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that thereby they might, the more mightely deceiue: and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience hath taught vs, that it hath byn the very vſe of ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>drie heretikes, as in old time of the Priſcilianiſtes, and in theſe dayes of the family of loue, to ſay and vnſaie. And therfore I wiſh the godlie Chriſtian to haue an eye to this, not onely to credite this or any other erroneous perſon, vppon a bare deniall of his or their vntruthes, but for the better ſifting of them, to require a plaine, and an open confeſſion, of the contrarie truthes and an yeelding therto, and then no doubte it ſhall ſufficiently appeare, whether the retracting of their errors, bee plaine and ſimple yea or no. Thus beſeeching the Lorde, to giue thoſe that be his, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in all thinges, that in
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:3475:80"/>ſound knowledge they may proue, what that good, holie, and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble good will of his is, and in bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed obedience, labour with care and conſcience, to performe the ſame, I ende, for this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. At London the 27. of this May. 1581.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ <hi>Jmprinted at London</hi> at the three cranes in the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree by Thomas Dawſon <hi>for Thomas Man. 1581.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
